<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-28T18:56:14+00:00</updated><id>https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Service Innovation Lab</title><subtitle>The Service Innovation Lab is an All-of-Government lab in Aotearoa New Zealand, hosting and enabling collaboration across agencies. We research, design, and develop ways to improve people’s experiences when they interact with government.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Recommendations Report</title><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/08/02/Rates-Rebates-Recommendations-Report/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recommendations Report" /><published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/08/02/Rates-Rebates-Recommendations-Report</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/08/02/Rates-Rebates-Recommendations-Report/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;executive-summary&quot;&gt;Executive Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Rates Rebate is a subsidy (currently up to $640) for low-income homeowners on the cost of their residential rates. The subsidy is delivered by Local Councils and is administered by Central Government (currently the Department of Internal Affairs (DIA)). The entitlement value is calculated by the cost of the rates, applicants income, and number of dependants. The maximum subsidy amount is reviewed yearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a successful (and &lt;a href=&quot;https://nzosa.org.nz/finalists2018/&quot;&gt;award winning&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/making-it-easier-the-rates-rebates-story-so-far/&quot;&gt;Alpha&lt;/a&gt; phase in May and September 2018, the Rates Rebate beta trial was run in June and July 2019 by a team with members from Service Delivery and Operations team within DIA, Government Information Services, and the Service Innovation Lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Service Innovation Lab invited three councils (Tauranga City Council, Hutt City Council, and Kāpiti Coast District Council) to participate from a larger group that expressed interest. The three councils each run a different IT system for processing applications, providing a good test of any proposed process changes, and a good indication of the challenges of rolling out the solution more widely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence gathered during the beta trial supported the observation during the Alpha phase that an optimised online application form takes just 4 minutes to complete on average, compared to 25 minutes for the paper form. Feedback from councils supported evidence gathered via observation that the online application was considered much easier for applicants to complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beta dramatically reduced per-transaction costs for councils, eliminating the need to courier paper applications between councils and the DIA. Councils have communicated their intention to actively promote the online option (if it proceeds beyond beta) based on the improved experience for applicants (and lower processing costs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statutory declaration remains the single biggest barrier preventing large scale adoption of an online application process (as well as a significant barrier to those applying on paper). Removing the statutory declaration removes the requirement to visit a council to submit an application. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/11gccvNrVD4PnfvMZwgwHEO4M5UQmRvjbpTZjBVA1lD8/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; was written to support the case for this change during the beta phase. If the case for change is supported, this requirement could be removed by June 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zDiJs8x2r9ABKa0hqCHkDZnK1B5iy-JlNSbtCZUoDuo/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Rates Rebate Beta Research Report&lt;/a&gt;, this report documents the key results of the trial, presents options for next steps, and makes a set of recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;high-level-recommendations&quot;&gt;High-level recommendations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A set of recommendations beyond beta are also included later in the document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;run-a-second-trial-with-the-existing-three-councils-during-a-high-application-volume-period-and-implement-data-export-solutions&quot;&gt;Run a second trial with the existing three councils during a high application volume period and implement data export solutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A second trial should be run during a high volume period (e.g. August and September) to fully inform DIA and Council decisions about next steps. While running the beta in June meant that council staff were available to collaborate and co-design improvements to the application and process, it also meant that application volumes were lower for councils than they would have been in July and August.
Evidence gathered during the Alpha (which ran through the busy period) suggests that uptake of the online option is high when it is promoted by councils (20% of the 800 recipients of a letter sent by Tauranga City Council promoting the online option opted to use it in 2018).
The councils involved in the trial have enthusiastically requested that the trial be extended through a high volume period.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The second trial should be limited to the same three councils who participated in June/July. This will enable valuable data to be gathered while keeping the cost of the extension minimal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delay the decision about whether to proceed beyond this extension until the end of this second trial. This will allow time for results from the first round to be validated against higher application volumes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improvements should be made to how data is transferred between the online application solution and council core systems, and options explored to improve data transfer between council systems and eRMS. The high trust relationship built with the councils involved in the trial should be leveraged to (co)design and implement simple, low cost (but high value) solutions during the trial extension period&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;options-to-consider&quot;&gt;Options to consider&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option 1 - &lt;strong&gt;Close down the initiative&lt;/strong&gt;: inform Councils there will be no change to the current paper-based service from DIA. Decommission the service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option 2 - &lt;strong&gt;Run a second trial with the existing three councils&lt;/strong&gt;. Continue to provide support, but limit other activity to keep costs minimal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option 3 - &lt;strong&gt;Run a second trial with the existing three councils through a high application volume period and implement data export solutions (recommended)&lt;/strong&gt;: proceed as for option two, but also implement data export solution for councils (for import into their core systems). Investigate (and document a recommendation for) the best solution to improve data submission (reduce cost and reduce/eliminate data entry errors) from council core systems to eRMS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option 4 - &lt;strong&gt;Extend the trial with the existing three councils until the end of June 2020&lt;/strong&gt;: continue to gradually evolve the service with these councils throughout this period. Use the high quality relationship built with councils to co-design the optimal online (and paper) application process ready for when the statutory declaration requirement is removed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option 5 - &lt;strong&gt;Extend the trial until the end of June 2020 and allow another three councils to join&lt;/strong&gt;: continue to run the trial with Tauranga City Council, Kāpiti District Council, and Hutt City Council through to June 2020 and trial the service with an additional three councils. Aim to sign up councils that will best test whether the service is ready to be rolled out nationally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rates Rebates Online Beta was designed to meet the needs of ratepayers, councils, and the DIA Rates Rebates team. It was built based on the findings of a Discovery and Alpha phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Discovery phase we mapped and reviewed the existing Rates Rebates delivery system. We interviewed internal and external stakeholders, and explored potential methods of service delivery. The discovery revealed many opportunities at the system level to improve the experience for both the people applying for their entitlement and people delivering the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Alpha phase, we designed and developed a minimum viable product (MVP), and trialled the product in Tauranga from 21 May—30 September 2018 with Tauranga City Council. The alpha focused on testing system changes. Tauranga City Council, Auckland Council assisted with the design and test of the alpha and numerous other councils watched progress closely. The Alpha proved to be of high value to ratepayers and Councils, and successfully tested a fully digital and user-centred end to end rates rebate process. The source code was released under an Open Source licence (MIT), and the project won the Award for Open Source Use in Government for 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Beta phase, we focused on further refining the service based on further user research and feedback from ratepayers and councils. We emphasised on ensuring it is was set up to be a live, fully functional, and sustainable system. This included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning how the service can scale to more than one council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving the alpha solution to sustainable production infrastructure and technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensuring accessibility, privacy, security issue standards for public services are fully adhered to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gathering feedback from beyond a wider range of councils, beyond just the single council involved in the alpha&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building a case for further investment and rule changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exploring options for future ownership of the service to ensure it will be well managed and continue to evolve if it progresses beyond beta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following research into current user behaviour, the online rates rebate application form was implemented within govt.nz (which is recognised as the authority on rates rebates by major search engines, and referenced by council websites).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User acceptance testing (UAT) for the Rates Rebate Beta began on Tuesday 21 May. The Beta trial with ratepayers started on Wednesday 5 June and ended on Monday 1 July. Councils continued to process online applications up to 1 August 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funding for the Beta was approved by the Service Innovation Working Group (SIWG) within the Digital Government Partnership supported by the Government Chief Digital Officer (GCDO). To deliver the Beta, a virtual team was created with support and participation from the Service Delivery and Operations (SDO) team (who continue to provide advice and subject matter expertise), and the Government Information Services (GIS) team (who made a significant contribution to the initiative by contributing two developers at high capacity for an extended period). At this stage there has been no funding approved to proceed beyond Beta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;current-factors-impacting-customers-using-the-service&quot;&gt;Current factors impacting customers using the service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low income, and time poor&lt;/strong&gt;
The current application process is complex, takes a long time, and places an unjustified burden on many people by asking for more information than is necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Issues affecting mobility and access&lt;/strong&gt;
The lack of an alternative, accessible way to make an application means many people who have a disability e.g. a vision impairment (&lt;a href=&quot;http://archive.stats.govt.nz/browse_for_stats/health/disabilities/DisabilitySurvey_HOTP2013/Commentary.aspx&quot;&gt;over 11% of those over 65&lt;/a&gt;) or a physical disability (&lt;a href=&quot;http://archive.stats.govt.nz/browse_for_stats/health/disabilities/DisabilitySurvey_HOTP2013/Commentary.aspx#impairtype&quot;&gt;49% of those over 65&lt;/a&gt; struggle to apply for help they are eligible to receive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of customers are over 65 and/or living with a disability. In the 2017/18 rating year 79% of all applicants were receiving New Zealand Superannuation. The requirement to sign a Statutory Declaration in front of a witness is a barrier for this group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: During the Beta trial, a separate paper &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/11gccvNrVD4PnfvMZwgwHEO4M5UQmRvjbpTZjBVA1lD8/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;“Why remove the statutory declaration”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; was written to support the case for its removal. This paper details the substantial benefits associated with removing the statutory declaration, when this is supported with adoption of an online application process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;applications-submitted-during-the-trial&quot;&gt;Applications submitted during the trial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We choose to run the beta during the quiet June period directly following the normal “reminder” sent out by councils before the end of the financial year. Councils indicated that this timing would work well because staff would be available to collaborate, co-design, and test improvements to the application and process. This worked well, with the design team able to work closely with both frontline and back office staff to observe processes and current practice. Council staff were also available during a two week period of user acceptance testing, which was important (we had received feedback from Tauranga that insufficient time had been allowed for user acceptance testing in the Alpha).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running the trial in the June period also meant that only a low number of applications were expected to be received and processed (this turned out to be the case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A total of 101 applications were submitted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;46 of the 101 applications were signed and fully processed.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;12 were processed by Tauranga City Council&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;8 were processed by Hutt City Council&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;26 were processed by Kāpiti District Council&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 of the 101 were submitted, but never signed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 of the 101 applications were declined.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The most common reason supplied by councils for declining applications was “income too high”. However, there were also a significant number of applications from ratepayers who had already applied in the 18/19 year.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The ability to “decline” an application (and supply a reason) was added to the beta, and we believe this feature could provide useful data for analysis (see “Recommendations beyond beta” section later in the document for more about this).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;expected-benefits&quot;&gt;Expected benefits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We expected the Rates Rebate Beta beta app to help people identify their eligibility and then apply for the rebate with less effort and stress. It was also designed to simplify service delivery for the council from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/rates-rebates-discovery-week-2-mapping-pain-points/&quot;&gt;the current very manual and paper-heavy process&lt;/a&gt; to a significantly simpler, faster (and digital) service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trial also further explored how uptake of the scheme could increased. The need to raise awareness of the scheme was identified in the Discovery and Alpha phase, and had recently prompted the DIA to write to the Royal New Zealand Returned and Services Association, Grey Power and the Citizens Advice Bureau in about eligibility and how to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integration between council and DIA systems was a pain point. We agreed with Service Delivery and Operations that this was not in scope for the trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, the beta was designed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the uptake of the Rates Rebate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve customer experience and satisfaction levels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decrease the cost of processing applications for councils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve the ability to digitally deliver this and other services to councils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support the case to remove the statutory declaration (witnessed signature requirement)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Produce insights informing other use cases with a similar customer profile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evidence-supporting-expected-benefits&quot;&gt;Evidence supporting expected benefits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-increase-the-uptake-of-the-rates-rebate&quot;&gt;1. Increase the uptake of the Rates Rebate**&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The removal of the statutory declaration requirement for an online application has been clearly identified as the key change needed to increase application volume. Removing the statutory declaration removes the barrier of having to visit a council to submit an application. A paper was written to support the case for this change during the beta phase. If successful, this requirement could be removed by June 2020. All three councils involved in the trial are convinced enabling applications to be completed online will result in a major increase in applications both received and processed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/rates-rebate-content-changes-lead-to-better-experience-more-users/&quot;&gt;Improvements were made to Rates Rebate content on govt.nz and the calculator&lt;/a&gt; based on the analysis of analytics data. These improvements resulted in a significant increase in the number of application form (PDF) downloads. The improvements also resulted in an increase in the number of people receiving an estimate when visiting the calculator (from 47% to 58%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The online application form was optimised to work on mobiles, tablets, and other common devices. The low volume of applications submitted during the trial meant that no meaningful conclusions can be drawn from analysis of analytics data (e.g. percentage of applicants using mobile devices - or, for example, when during the day these applications were filled in). A second trial during a high volume period is recommended to gather more data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The online application form was designed to be a lot simpler than the paper version, which (based on observations by the team and councils) substantially reduced the effort required to complete an application. There is no baseline to compare this to because this isn’t tracked for paper applications (they may be simply discarded). At this stage analytics data measuring conversion hasn’t been processed given the low volumes of applications received during the trial. This will be completed if a further trial is run during a higher volume period. Improvements to the form included:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;questions reworded&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;questions reordered&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;unnecessary questions and repetition removed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;in-context help content provided&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The online application form is much faster to complete, it took on average 4 minutes for customers to complete, versus 25 minutes for the paper form. Again, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zDiJs8x2r9ABKa0hqCHkDZnK1B5iy-JlNSbtCZUoDuo/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;research indicated&lt;/a&gt; this resulted in greater completion rates, but there is no baseline established for paper application forms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Councils are aware that an online application is much faster to complete than a paper application (and much faster for them to process) and they intend to promote this option as a result (if the trial proceeds beyond beta).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A great deal of care was taken to ensure the application form is accessible for those with disabilities. This work has been completed with GIS accessibility expert Jason Kiss. With approximately 11% of the target audience vision impaired, and 59% with a disability of some kind, this should not be considered an optional extra (as highlighted in the recently published &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/digital-government/digital-transformation/digital-inclusion/digital-inclusion-blueprint/&quot;&gt;Digital Inclusion Blueprint&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m partially blind, so if things are on a computer I can zoom in and read them”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Sorry, my fingers don’t work very well”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Trouble is I can’t walk very far now. My knees and my ankles have packed up. I can’t drive …because my shoulder’s packed”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was evidence gathered during the trial that even when applicants need to switch channels to apply online, they will do so. Tauranga sent out 800 final reminder letters and had 20% online.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As part of the beta trial, email addresses were requested from applicants so that a confirmation email could be sent to confirm their application had been received. These email addresses provide an opportunity to remind applicants to apply in subsequent years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-improve-customer-experience-and-satisfaction-levels---decrease-time-effort-and-stress&quot;&gt;2. Improve customer experience and satisfaction levels - decrease time, effort and stress**&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The online application form takes on average &lt;strong&gt;4 minutes to complete, versus 25 minutes for the paper form.&lt;/strong&gt; This improvement was observed during the Alpha, and supported by observations and analytics during the beta trial. This is a huge improvement which we believe had a huge influence on the overwhelming positive customer feedback gathered by councils (who set up surveys in their offices using existing kiosks, and interviewed applicants).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The people that came in to complete the online process thought it was really good. Clearly an easier process for them”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Moira Aplin (Rates Officer, Hutt City Council)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While there may be no accepted way of calculating the dollar value of saving 19 minutes for every application filled out, this is a significant time saving for people who we know (from our user research) are time poor - especially if/when it can be realised for a large proportion of the over 95,000 applications submitted annually.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We know from user research that ratepayers find the current paper application form confusing. This leads to forms often being completed incorrectly, or required fields left blank.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We also know that when this happens, and the problems aren’t picked up at the counter, the applicant must be contacted and the application re-submitted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This delays when the rebate is granted at a time when it’s needed most. Feedback from councils indicated that they experienced fewer of these problems with the application forms they received online.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is still plenty of room for improvement however. The ability to move applications into a “Declined” state (and state a reason) was added based on feedback from councils. A much higher number of applications were moved into this declined state than expected. The most common reasons for declining applications were “applicant had already applied that year” and “applicants income was too high”. This suggests that there is confusion about when to apply. It also suggests (and this was supported by feedback from Tauranga City Council in particular) that there wasn’t enough done in the application process to warn applicants that they may not be eligible based on the information they have supplied before they make the trip to sign their application at a council office. There is more about this in “Recommendations beyond beta” later in this document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-decrease-the-cost-of-processing-applications-for-councils&quot;&gt;3. Decrease the cost of processing applications for councils&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bigger councils currently spend hundreds of thousands of dollars on serving and administering the rebate for rate payers (e.g. Tauranga City Council estimate it costs them $200,000 annually to process 4,500 applications).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even smaller councils like Carterton District Council process 2,000-3,000 applications each year. Councils in the Wairarapa told us they work nights and weekends during the busy period to meet demand - and they believe they currently have very low uptake. They said that “anything to make the experience better” would be a massive help.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Beta has dramatically reduced the cost per transaction costs by:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Validating all required fields are filled in&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Providing guidance and validation messages to ensure the fields are filled in correctly&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improving the quality of addresses by suggesting addresses from council rates data&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Removing the need to manage and review evidence of income documentation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Removing the need to review dependant details&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Automatically filling in rates values and valuation IDs based on council data&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Removing the need to key in applications from hand-written paper application forms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reducing the time that the double signature step takes by automatically filling in the council staff name, date, and the applicant’s occupation - and capturing signatures digitally&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improving the back-office workflow by supporting the ability to easily mark applications as “Processed” and “Batched”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Completely removing the need to collate and courier paper applications to DIA&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feedback from councils on the improvements made during the beta include:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I can’t emphasise how much better the experience is … the experience is smooth and the QR code is a bit special.”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Jeremy Glass (Team Leader: Service Centre, Tauranga City Council)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The speed of the transaction is really noticeable. For example, removing the need for ratepayers to provide evidence of income has made a huge difference.”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Jeremy Glass (Team Leader: Service Centre, Tauranga City Council)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Signing of the applications and the processing has all gone smoothly… I’ve really enjoyed not having lots of paperwork on my desk - not having to work out which bits of paper go with which bits of paper… I would love to see this system go ahead.”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Moira Aplin (Rates Officer, Hutt City Council)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The look up fields for address worked well and the annual rates amount pulled through to the Council view, so that’s great!”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Council back office team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I was buzzing after yesterday’s conference call… [you] have achieved big wins in this phase… Awesome. You have taken the administration of the act back as was originally intended. Not needing proof or collecting unnecessary information is huge for us, and presumably the back office in the rebate team.”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Jim Taylor (Manager Transactional Services, Tauranga City Council)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“R% said even the signature part is great. She has had applications returned that she signed but had not printed her name, valueless bureaucracy. I love that you are implementing transformational change rather than plastering over the cracks”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Jim Taylor (Manager Transactional Services, Tauranga City Council)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Based on their experience to date in the Beta trial, Tauranga City Council provided scenarios for the cost savings associated with moving applications online. These scenarios &lt;strong&gt;do not&lt;/strong&gt; include the savings they believe will be realised if/when the statutory declaration requirement is removed.
Cost to process:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current state&lt;/strong&gt;: 4,500 paper applications = $200,000&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approx 45% online&lt;/strong&gt;: 2,500 paper + 2,000 online applications = $125,000&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All online&lt;/strong&gt;: 4,500 online applications = $75,000&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we assume that the cost per application reduces as the number of applications increases for a given council, then taking Tauranga’s cost per paper application (one of the larger councils) is likely to be conservative = 200,000/4,500 = &lt;strong&gt;$44&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In Tauranga’s scenario where 45% of applications are completed online, they estimate savings of over $35 per application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tauranga have also reported that when they sent out 800 reminder letters, they had 20% of applications completed online.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we assume…
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we can shift 20% of all applications online&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;save $30 in processing cost per application completed online&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;there were many more applications submitted and processed in some way than the 97,510 that were successful in 2017/2018 (as shown in the trial many applications are declined, are duplicates etc)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;..then we can conclude that the total savings for all councils nationwide in the first year would be substantially greater than $35 × 97,510 × 20% = &lt;strong&gt;$682,570&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This number would be expected to increase as the proportion of applicants applying online increases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-improve-the-ability-to-digitally-deliver-this-and-other-services-to-councils&quot;&gt;4. Improve the ability to digitally deliver this and other services to councils&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One of the most important questions that the Beta phase set out to answer was “will councils even agree to participate in a beta trial”, given their participation involved a significant amount of time and effort on their part. The response we received from the councils we invited/pitched to participate was overwhelmingly positive. In fact, demand to participate in the Beta trial far exceeded expectations, and some councils were informed that they would need to wait to see if there was a subsequent Beta phase.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Representatives from all three councils are so enthusiastic about the results of the trial that they are keen to get an opportunity to personally (face to face) provide their feedback on the trial to Rates Rebate decision makers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A high trust relationship has been built with the councils involved in the trial, with really positive feedback from all three councils (see #3 above).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As part of the trial, digital tools such as Trello and Slack were introduced to council staff. These tools enabled transparent and swift communication throughout the trial, and also encouraged communication between councils.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The trial involved the council experiencing rapid cycles of development and feedback which could from the basis for other similar engagements with those councils.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The virtual team model where a team was formed from SDO, GIS, and the Service Innovation Lab proved to be a highly effective mechanism to rapidly improve a service. The combination of subject (service) matter expertise, digital channel expertise (and access + control of the channel/platform), and service design meant implementation was extremely efficient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-support-the-case-to-remove-the-statutory-declaration-witnessed-signature-requirement&quot;&gt;5. Support the case to remove the statutory declaration (witnessed signature requirement)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A paper was written to support the case for this change during the beta phase. A summary of the key points is included here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Applying for a rates rebate currently involves making a statutory declaration. The requirement to have applicants have their signature witnessed to complete a rates rebate application means that they are unable to submit an application without travelling either to a council office, or organising an alternative witness, such as a JP.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The need to travel necessitated by the statutory declaration has been identified as the biggest single barrier preventing large scale adoption of an online application process. It is also considered the biggest hurdle for those submitting paper based applications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While this step may seem a minor inconvenience for those who live or work close to a council office, and who are mobile, it is a major barrier for those in more remote locations, or those who are less mobile, such as the disabled and the elderly. It is likely that these are some of the most disadvantaged in our communities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Removal of the statutory declaration, and adoption of the online application process will…
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;remove a substantial cost and inconvenience barrier for those who don’t live near a council office&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;enable people who are actually unable to travel to council offices to still apply for a rebate&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;allow the process to scale beyond the availability and capacity of council staff to witness signatures and support paper based applications&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;significantly reduce the costs of administering the scheme through the removal of manual tasks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support improvements to privacy within the application process. It is not practical to control or record who views information provided on paper. When applications are made online, there are opportunities to remove and/or audit council staff access to private information supplied in the application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-produce-insights-informing-other-use-cases-with-a-similar-customer-profile&quot;&gt;6. Produce insights informing other use cases with a similar customer profile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Beta phase was focused on further refining the Alpha service based on further user research and feedback from ratepayers and three councils. The Rates Rebate Research Report documents insights from research based on a combination of customer interviews, council and stakeholder observations and conversations, online surveys and analytics analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The key insights from this report are:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The system is too complex and multiple errors are occuring&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Seniors are more digitally capable than many assume&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Applicants are relinquishing control over to the council and authorities&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The current process is not accessible to people with disabilities&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Retirement village residents were well supported and have wrap around services&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There is a significant appetite for various forms of automation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Eligible applicants are not applying because their personal data is not private&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The statutory declaration is a significant barrier to the completion of the process&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There is a need for human contact and support&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Newly bereaved need additional help with the application process&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Leverage the best channels for awareness and support&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many of these insights inform other use cases with a similar customer profiles. Rates Rebate is just one example of a service used by seniors. Two examples of insights which inform services beyond Rates Rebate are:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seniors are more digitally capable than many assume&lt;/strong&gt;
Many superannuitants are using websites and apps to achieve a wide range of tasks. Three quarters of the superannuitants interviewed are interacting online and are digitally savvy. Facebook, Skype and emails are commonly used to connect friends and family. A large proportion use these applications for video calling, sharing photos, and sending messages.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The current process is not accessible to people with disabilities&lt;/strong&gt;
The applicants interviewed all used reading glasses and struggled to read the smaller text on the paper application form. If the application form is accessed as a downloadable pdf, it’s possible to enlarge the text, but the content doesn’t reflow into the screen, therefore comprehension is compromised. The downloadable pdf hasn’t been tagged with appropriate markup labels, therefore is not accessible to those using screen reader technology.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommendations-beyond-beta&quot;&gt;Recommendations beyond beta&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on what was learned during the beta trial, we recommend the following areas be explored further:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider a substantial redesign of the paper application form and/or alternative ways to apply.&lt;/strong&gt; Ratepayers find the current paper application form confusing. This leads to forms often being completed incorrectly, or required fields left blank. Applicants often perceive the ‘rates’ and ‘income’ step as easy, yet will frequently get this information wrong. Accessibility is also a real problem. All of the applicants interviewed during or research used reading glasses and struggled to read the smaller text on the paper application form.
There is more information about this in the Rates Rebate Beta Research Report (key insight #1 and #4 - with detail in Appendix 2).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ensure councils understand their role in the application process, in particular with respect to the declaration and income.&lt;/strong&gt; Research conducted during the beta trial found there is a lack of clarity around the role council staff have in authenticating the proof of income. This can mean that the responsibility of verification frequently falls to the council staff member, rather than the ownership of the declaration staying with the applicant.
The beta trial tested the removal of the need to supply evidence of income. This reduced the level of effort required by councils to process some applications. It also made it very clear whose responsibility it was to ensure the declaration of income was correct. We saw evidence during the trial which suggested that application details (including) were regularly being updated after declarations were being signed. This is clearly not good practice.
There is more information about this in the Rates Rebate Beta Research Report (key insight #3).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explore how the application forms might be pre-filled based on previous applications.&lt;/strong&gt; Results from surveys (29 of 33 respondents) and interviews indicate that the majority of applicants would prefer to have the form prefilled based on their previous application. Eligible ratepayers are surprised that they are required to fill in the form manually every year. This perplexes a lot of people as they find repeating the process of getting the information from separate government authorities inefficient and a waste of time. People’s circumstances don’t generally change each year, yet the same information is required every rating year.
There is more information about this in the Rates Rebate Beta Research Report (key insight #6).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conduct further research during the 19/20 rating year into how well the application process is working for retirement village residents.&lt;/strong&gt; Our research found that the experience of village residents who had applied in 18/19 was very positive, but we believe this is because local councils provided a high level of support in the first year, which is unlikely to be the case from the second year onwards.
There is more information about this in the Rates Rebate Beta Research Report (key insight #5).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leverage the high trust relationship built with the three councils involved in the trial to (co)design and implement simple, low cost (but high value) solutions.&lt;/strong&gt; These include:
 a. &lt;strong&gt;Providing data exports for online applications which can be imported into council systems.&lt;/strong&gt; During the trial a basic example was implemented to solicit feedback from councils, but there wasn’t sufficient time to refine the solution.
 b. &lt;strong&gt;Explore how to best extend the solution to support applicants who live in retirement villages.&lt;/strong&gt; A decision was made during the beta to focus on optimising the process for the majority of applicants, and not attempt to support retirement villages. A solution for retirement village residents (and in particular providing a solution to allow village administrators to submit the additional supplementary information) was explored during the trial, and is not expected to be particularly hard to fully design and implement.
 c. &lt;strong&gt;Design a solution which provides guidance about the rebate the applicant can expect as part of the application process (rather than requiring applicants to use the calculator first).&lt;/strong&gt; An estimated value of the rebate likely to be received was removed from the alpha after feedback from councils suggested that the majority of applicants entered either their rates or their income values incorrectly, and may be put off completing their application if they saw an incorrect estimate displayed. Tauranga believe that this led to a number of unnecessary visits by applicants who were not eligible. We believe it is possible to design a solution which carefully communicates the rebate is an estimate - not putting off those struggling to get the figures correct from seeking help, but also preventing unnecessary trips by those clearly not eligible.
 d. Explore other small changes which will reduce back office processing effort for councils. Kāpiti were unable to process online applications together with paper applications during the trial which required additional management effort.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improve the “Decline” feature in the application which allows applications to be put in “declined” state (and stores a reason why the application was declined).&lt;/strong&gt; This simple feature could be easily enhanced to suggest a list of common reasons applications are rejected when councils reject applications. This would then facilitate easy analysis of this data by SDO.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explore the value that could be provided by implementing a simple dashboard that gives senior council staff an overview of how many applications are at which stage of the workflow. Also explore whether providing this information to DIA, and an additional view across all councils would be valuable.&lt;/strong&gt; During the beta there was evidence to suggest that many problems occured in the paper process when applications were not processed in a timely fashion. The ability to monitor the workflow was highlighted by both councils and SDO as a desirable feature.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement improvements to the layout of the application batch files provided for DIA by the beta application.&lt;/strong&gt; While there were a number of refinements made to the batch file format based on feedback from the Service Delivery and Operations team, there are a simple improvements (such as better support for double sided printing) which could be easily implemented and make a big difference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Replace the need to print and file paper copies of applications for 7 years with a digital alternative.&lt;/strong&gt; In the beta trial a solution was implemented which created application batch files which could be printed by Service Delivery and Operations direct from the secure application. This achieved the goal of avoiding the need for councils to print and then courier these batch files, while minimising any impact on the SDO team. There is an opportunity to explore existing digital solutions within DIA/government which meet the 7 year requirement for storage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement a solution that supports the rejection of applications which have already been lodged in eRMS.&lt;/strong&gt; The process for paper applications currently involves rejecting a claim in eRMS, and then returning the form to the council to have the application amended, resigned, and submitted in a new batch. The equivalent process has not yet been implemented in the beta.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explore whether introducing rules-based auditing (in addition to the current audit process) would make the process more robust.&lt;/strong&gt; In the beta applicants weren’t required to supply evidence of income. If they declared income under $5,000 they were asked to supply a reason. Rules/triggers (e.g. declared less than $5,000 income) which prompt further information to be requested in certain cases may be an opportunity to make the process more robust while keeping most applications lean.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measure the improvements to the DIA part of the process as a result of a move from paper on online applications. Explore further opportunities to reduce costs.&lt;/strong&gt; Improvements to data quality through the elimination of errors when interpreting handwriting, and during keying in applications, will reduce issues for DIA as well as councils. Reducing the number of applications couriered should also reduce effort. Greater visibility of council workflows is likely to increase the ability to capacity plan, and reduce peaks and troughs. This value should be measured, and optimised.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work with Inland Revenue and Ministry of Social Development to allow for consented income testing to make it easier for applicants to prove their income.&lt;/strong&gt; Despite applicants often perceiving the ‘rates’ and ‘income’ step as easy, it is known that they frequently get this information wrong. The beta used rates information supplied by councils to remove errors with rates information, this left income as the major pain point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work with other agencies such as Ministry of Social Development to integrate the rates rebate application into applications for other services.&lt;/strong&gt; The product owner of MyMSD was engaged during the beta trial and there was interest in working together to paper prototype potential solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Translate the online application form into other languages, and provide the option online to choose a language.&lt;/strong&gt; Councils identified that they had applicants who had low levels of fluency in English and found applying difficult. It was common for the council teams to find a workmate who spoke the language and could deal with these applications, and also for these staff to move on leaving the teams unable to deal with applicants with low English fluency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>glen-thurston</name></author><category term="blog post" /><category term="open source" /><category term="rates rebate" /><category term="te whakamāmā i ngā reiti" /><summary type="html">Following a successful Alpha phase in May and September 2018, the Rates Rebate beta trial was run in June and July 2019 by a team with members from Service Delivery and Operations team within DIA, Government Information Services, and the Service Innovation Lab. This was in collaboration with Tauranga City Council, Hutt City Council, and Kāpiti Coast District Council</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Testing our Toolkit</title><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/31/Testing-Our-Toolkit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Testing our Toolkit" /><published>2019-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/31/Testing-Our-Toolkit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/31/Testing-Our-Toolkit/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;tests-we-run&quot;&gt;Tests we run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This toolkit is built using an open-source tool called Jekyll. We write content in markdown format, which is then parsed by Jekyll which produces a static HTML website that we host on Github pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content and other changes are proposed by team members using the pull requests on Github. There are a bunch of automated tests the proposed change must satisfy to be accepted (as well as manual testing). The automated tests are fast and means the pull request is in good shape by the time a team member begins their peer review. The tests catch many of our mistakes, as well as being an easy way to learn about content standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/testing.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flow diagram of our tests&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-tests&quot;&gt;Our Tests&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use a continuous integration service called &lt;a href=&quot;https://circleci.com/&quot;&gt;CircleCI&lt;/a&gt; to run our tests. CircleCI is an open-source tool and is available to us for free because our projects are also Open Source (as per &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.data.govt.nz/manage-data/policies/nzgoal/nzgoal-se/&quot;&gt;NZGOAL&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;yamllint&quot;&gt;yamllint&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YAML is a standard format for configuration files (and also the name of Brenda’s cat). Jekyll uses YAML, so we use a linter to inspect our files.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://yamllint.readthedocs.io/en/stable/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;yamllint&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.org/project/yamllint/&quot;&gt;python tool available on pip&lt;/a&gt;. It catches any strange/incorrect indenting with better and more helpful errors messages than the tool that reads those YAML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;build&quot;&gt;build&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CI builds the static content on every pull request to ensure that once your change it merged into mainline (the dev branch) it can be successfully built for deployment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;markdownlint&quot;&gt;markdownlint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/markdownlint/markdownlint&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;markdownlint&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a linter that checks you have followed our style guide for markdown files. The linter catches when you’re using &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt; instead of headers. It fails your pull request if you don’t put descriptions on images if it’s not clear which are the header cells on a table, and if your header nesting doesn’t make sense in a tree structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;percy&quot;&gt;percy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://percy.io&quot;&gt;Percy&lt;/a&gt; is a service that takes screenshots of every page and compares them to the previous screenshot. If there are differences (i.e. you’ve modified a page on the toolkit) you’ll need to go to Percy and then view and approve the changes. If you’ve broken the display on a page, you’ll see it in the screenshots (and of course if you’ve broken a page, don’t approve it!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accessibility&quot;&gt;accessibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accessibility check uses a tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pa11y/pa11y-ci&quot;&gt;pa11y-ci&lt;/a&gt; to check we adhere to WCAG21 standard. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/standards-and-guidance/nz-government-web-standards/web-accessibility-standard-1-1/&quot;&gt;New Zealand Government - Web Accessibility Standard 1.1&lt;/a&gt; is based on WCAG21. This linter is configured by a file named &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.pa11yci.json&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automated tests catch common mistakes quickly, and more thoroughly than our manual testing. A linter can give quick feedback on proposed changes before the author asks another team member for their peer review. With automated content testing, we can get better quality markup on our toolkit pages, and with a quicker publishing turnaround.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a pull request the checks look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/pull_request.png&quot; alt=&quot;github screen shot, showing passing, failing, and pending checks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>brenda-wallace</name></author><category term="open source" /><category term="tech" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rates Rebate Beta - Research Report</title><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/30/Rates-Rebate-Beta-Research-Report/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rates Rebate Beta - Research Report" /><published>2019-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/30/Rates-Rebate-Beta-Research-Report</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/30/Rates-Rebate-Beta-Research-Report/">&lt;p&gt;The research was conducted throughout the Beta project from February to June 2019. The research was a combination of customer interviews, council and stakeholder observations and conversations, online surveys and analytics analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content&quot;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-ExecutiveSummary&quot;&gt;Executive Summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-MethodsandOutputs&quot;&gt;Methods and Outputs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-insights&quot;&gt;Key insights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-KeyInsight-1&quot;&gt;The system is too complex and multiple errors are occuring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-KeyInsight-2&quot;&gt;Seniors are more digitally capable than many assume&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-KeyInsight-3&quot;&gt;Applicants are relinquishing control over to the council and authorities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-KeyInsight-4&quot;&gt;The current process is not accessible to people with disabilities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-KeyInsight-5&quot;&gt;Retirement village residents were well supported and have wrap around services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-KeyInsight-6&quot;&gt;There is a significant appetite for various forms of automation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-KeyInsight-7&quot;&gt;Eligible applicants are not applying because their personal data is not private&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-KeyInsight-8&quot;&gt;The statutory declaration is a significant barrier to the completion of the process&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-KeyInsight-9&quot;&gt;There is a need for human contact and support&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-KeyInsight-10&quot;&gt;Newly bereaved need additional help with the application process&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-KeyInsight-11&quot;&gt;Leverage the best channels for awareness and support&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;appendix&quot;&gt;Appendix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-AutomationFeedback&quot;&gt;Automation feedback&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-CompletingPaperForm&quot;&gt;Completing the paper application form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-FrequentlyUsedChannels&quot;&gt;Frequently used channels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-InSummary&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;executive-summary&quot;&gt;Executive Summary&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-ExecutiveSummary&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rates Rebate scheme provides a rebate of rates to eligible ratepayers to assist low-income households. The process is administered by local councils, who are then refunded by central government. The final amount of rebate available to an applicant is calculated by their household income, their total rates bill, and the number of dependants in the household.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Service Innovation Lab were commissioned to work on this initiative and completed a Discovery and Alpha phase. It was identified during the Alpha phase that deeper research and engagement was required to understand the barriers to completion, and how to improve uptake of the entitlement. This research informed the recent Beta phase of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design research was a combination of surveys, analytics and face to face interviews with the applicants and council staff. The research has informed ways to improve the access to the application, and to remove barriers to completion. We have been able to use the results of this research to restructure the online content on govt.nz. We have also been able to advise the DIA Service Delivery and Operations team on how improvements can be made to the existing paper application form to increase legibility, comprehension and accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve identified areas of improvements that can be made to the design of the end to end service to reduce errors, to improve accuracy, accessibility, privacy and efficiency of processing. These improvements will reduce cost and burden on the applicants, council and DIA teams. This also helps move towards delivering on the intent of the Rates Rebate Act. The biggest identified barrier to completion remains the requirement of the Statutory Declaration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The elderly are very susceptible to winter illnesses, and yet they often come out of their sick beds and warm houses to sign.” COUNCIL STAFF MEMBER&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research has helped us understand this audience segment and their trust and perception of government and local council. It has also challenged our initial assumptions about the digital capability of this segment, and have proven that this group are more digitally savvy than perhaps expected by many. They also have a high expectation of interacting online. This research has also informed us on how to better engage with this group with style of language, content structure, and the channels and communities in which to reach them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve identified the friction with processing retirement village applications through the councils, and the current work arounds, and foresee a reduction in uptake across retirement villages in the next rating year. This is something that can be integrated and improved with future iterations of Rates Rebate online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Background&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-rates-rebate&quot;&gt;What is Rates Rebate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rates Rebate scheme provides a rebate of rates to eligible ratepayers to assist low-income households. The process is administered by local councils, who are then refunded by central government. Applicants need to apply every year by providing an application form and proof of income to their local council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The maximum rebate available is currently set at $640. The final amount of rebate available to an applicant is calculated by their household income, their total rates bill, and the number of dependants in the household.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-applies-for-a-rates-rebate&quot;&gt;Who applies for a Rates Rebate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most recipients of a Rates Rebate are superannuitants. In the 2017/18 rating year &lt;strong&gt;79% of all successful applicants were receiving New Zealand Superannuation&lt;/strong&gt;. Other recipients were 14% employed, 4% on other benefits and 2% unemployed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2018 the Rates Rebate Amendment Act 2018 was passed. This amendment grants those who live in retirement villages eligibility to receive rates rebates (in the form of a refund). As a result of this change, uptake is expected to increase in coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total number of ratepayers eligible for a rates rebate is not known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-work-has-been-done-by-the-lab-for-rates-rebate&quot;&gt;What work has been done by the Lab for Rates Rebate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lab produced and tested an Alpha prototype with Tauranga City Council between May and September 2018. The Alpha proved to be of high value to ratepayers and Councils, and successfully tested a fully digital and user centred end to end rates rebate process. It was identified during this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/making-it-easier-the-rates-rebates-story-so-far/&quot;&gt;Alpha phase&lt;/a&gt; that deeper research and engagement was required to understand the barriers to completion, and how to improve uptake of the entitlement. This would help the team understand the nuances of this group and to understand the cultural attitudes around receiving money or help from institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Beta phase focused on further refining the service based on further user research and feedback from ratepayers and three councils. This report is a summary of the research findings with applicants and council staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-MethodsandOutputs&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;research-questions&quot;&gt;Research Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two primary areas being explored with the Rates Rebate beta were; could a solution like this increase uptake of the Rates Rebate, and could it improve customer experience and satisfaction levels (also the Outputs section for more). In order to inform solution design, both for the beta phase and beyond, we determined we needed answers to the following questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the current state of awareness?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the best channels for awareness and completion?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the digital capability of this cohort?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is confusing?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What creates blocks to completion?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the costs (including time, money, cognitive load, dignity)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A variety of research methods were used to get the information we needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-interviews-with-applicants&quot;&gt;1. Interviews with applicants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2019 we conducted interviews with nine eligible Tauranga ratepayers, over five days. Tauranga City Council helped us identify people we could interview that covered both the majority of eligible customers, and edge cases. The interviewees were recruited by Tauranga City Council, based on residents who had previously applied for a Rates Rebate, and therefore were a fair representation of those eligible and apply for a rates rebate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eight of the interviewees were over 65 and receiving superannuation. One interviewee was receiving an alternative benefit. The interviewees were a mix of people who lived in retirement villages and their own homes. They included people with English as a second language, and people with reduced mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The semi-structured interviews ran for 1.5 hours, and were conducted in people’s homes, retirement village rooms, and the local library. The interview process was a mix of visual cards to prompt dialog on current and future states, card sorting to reveal degrees of difficulty in the process, and potential supporting channels, filling in the existing paper application to identify what is confusing and a barrier to completion. Interviews were recorded by dictaphone, and photos taken of relevant steps. The recordings have been transcribed for analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-conversations-with-council-staff--department-internal-affairs&quot;&gt;2. Conversations with council staff &amp;amp; Department Internal Affairs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversations were conducted with Tauranga City Council, Hutt City Council, and Kāpiti District Council throughout the Beta phase. We observed the processing of applications at each council, and the unique system each council used. Additional conversations were held with Wairarapa councils to understand their process and pain points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked alongside subject matter experts from Rates Rebates team, within the Service Delivery and Operations branch at DIA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-online-surveys&quot;&gt;3. Online surveys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey research targeted existing visitors to the Rates Rebates section of govt.nz. Two surveys ran during the Beta project. The initial survey ran for two weeks at the start of the project, before any changes had been made to the content. A follow up survey ran for three weeks during the Beta trial to gauge visitors perception of the process and the changes implemented on the online application form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-analytics-analysis&quot;&gt;4. Analytics analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identified a set of data that we could pull from analytics on the original Rates Rebates section of govt.nz. This helped us understand current baseline behaviour, search patterns and plan appropriate content structure. The process and the results of this are available as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/rates-rebate-content-changes-lead-to-better-experience-more-users/&quot;&gt;blog: ‘Rates Rebate - content changes lead to better experience, more users’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outputs&quot;&gt;Outputs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;synthesis&quot;&gt;Synthesis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we had gathered all the data, we went through multiple steps of analysis and outputs. Because this activity was conducted in parallel with the Beta build, we were only able to implement improvements based on early insights immediately into the design of the service. Additional insights have surfaced as we have put the Beta online trial into production. It is hoped these can drive further improvements beyond Beta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-results-from-this-research-inform-how-we-might&quot;&gt;The results from this research inform how we might&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Help increase the uptake of the Rates Rebate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve customer experience and satisfaction levels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decrease the cost of processing applications for councils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve the ability to digitally deliver this and other services to councils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support the case to remove the statutory declaration (witnessed signature) requirement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reuse these insights for other use cases that have similar customer profiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report was produced in parallel with the &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/08/02/Rates-Rebates-Recommendations-Report/&quot;&gt;Rates Rebates Beta Recommendations Report&lt;/a&gt; which documents the key results of the trial, presents options for next steps, and makes a set of recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-insight-1&quot;&gt;Key insight #1&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system is too complex and multiple errors are occuring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ratepayers find the current paper application form confusing. This leads to forms often being completed incorrectly, or required fields left blank. Applicants often perceive the ‘rates’ and ‘income’ step as easy, yet will frequently get this information wrong. Councils suspect there are a large number of ratepayers not applying because the process is so daunting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rates amount required is a combination of local, regional and water rates which differ across regions. Applicants rarely have this information at hand, and can misinterpret what is needed. Councils have requested the rates field to be removed completely from the application form, as staff were continually correcting this data. Occasionally the information will be corrected after the statutory declaration has been signed. Retirement village residents don’t know how much they pay in rates, and rely on the village administrators to provide additional information to allow them to complete the application process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The income amount required is the total income from the previous year, before tax. Applicants often enter their income based on what appears in their bank account, then do a rough calculation to add it up to a year. This results in an inaccurate amount. Income amounts for benefits change depending on the year and individual circumstances, and very few people know the exact amount. DIA have supplied an income guide to councils to assist in helping applicants fill in the amounts. Having a list of possible incomes was helpful as a checklist prompt for applicants, but some didn’t know which benefit category they were in. Some didn’t bother to declare interest on investments because they considered the amounts too small to be relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m thinking, surely you want to know what I actually get, not what was there before tax”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Proof of income - that was blimmin hard”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of Dependants was commonly misunderstood by both applicants and council staff. This meant that applicants may miss claiming for a dependant family member who live in their household. This can impact their eligibility for a rebate. Details about a dependant are not legally required by the Act, and asking for this data may add a barrier to completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple dates in the application are difficult to understand and remember. A lot of people enter information for the wrong year. Some applicants mistakenly apply more than once a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-insight-2&quot;&gt;Key insight #2&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seniors are more digitally capable than many assume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Superannuitants are using websites and apps to achieve a wide range of tasks. There is high use of PCs, laptops, tablets and mobile phones in this demographic. Interaction online allows the applicants to apply in their own time and at their own pace. The barrier identified is access to the hardware and internet services rather than the ability to use digital systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three quarters of the superannuitants interviewed are interacting online and are digitally savvy. Facebook, Skype and emails are commonly used to connect friends and family. A large proportion use these applications for video calling, sharing photos, and sending messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google is used for searching and map locations. Appointments, sports games and holiday accommodation were booked online. Tracking apps were used to measure fitness and performance in walking and golf. Purchases were made through Trademe and Amazon. Ancestry was also used to explore and track genealogy. Various surveys, competitions and special offers were completed online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Google is amazing what you can find” “It needs to be simple”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“The iPad is just part of me -  it sits next to me in the arm chair”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Even oldies have got their phone - what would you do without it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online banking is popular, but this demographic were also very wary of sharing their bank details online due to a lot of publicity about scamming. Retirement village residents have no problem writing their bank account details on the paper declaration form for the application process. This is because there is a high level of trust that authorities will keep their information safe. Further testing will be needed to investigate comfort levels if bank account details are required for the online process, when village residents are applying for a refund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial constraints were stated as a barrier to either replacing technology that had stopped working, or buying a new mobile phone or tablet. The main requirements of using digital devices and systems is that it needs to be easy, and the users need to be in control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-insight-3&quot;&gt;Key insight #3&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applicants are passing over control of their application to council and authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Councils inform us that applicants often leave required fields or entire application form empty, and trust that council staff will enter or edit details correctly on their behalf. Although the applicants are signing the statutory declaration, they are doing so because they have a high level of trust in the decisions made by their local council staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application process is often seen as being complicated, so applicants often allow council to guide them through the application, and make suggested inputs and changes. There is a lack of clarity around the role council staff have in authenticating the proof of income. This can mean that the responsibility of verification frequently falls to the council staff member, rather than the ownership of the declaration staying with the applicant. There are some applicants who will leave a large folder with documentation, expecting the council to check complex account details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have heard from these customers that they need financial security, freedom, and to be in control of decision making. They like to track what has been done and when, and keep a paper trail of the process. This contrasts with the ease in which they are handing control over to other entities and authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s just government stuff. I’m not bothered. I’m past it now, you know, caring”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They don’t question those perceived as authorities. They have a high level of trust in local council and government, trust in the retirement village operators, and trust advice given by their accountants and lawyers. There is a lack of need to understand the complexity of the process, and a level of comfort in passing the decisions over to other authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A lot of it was done for us. It just made it really really easy”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retirement village residents relied on the village administrators to provide the additional  supplementary form information. There were some applications that were stalled at council, unable to be processed, because the retirement village administrators had not provided the additional paperwork. There is no guarantee that these forms will be supplied to allow the application to be processed, and the applicants to receive their reimbursement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-insight-4&quot;&gt;Key insight #4&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current process is not accessible to people with disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With approximately &lt;a href=&quot;http://archive.stats.govt.nz/browse_for_stats/health/disabilities/DisabilitySurvey_HOTP2013/Commentary.aspx&quot;&gt;11% of the target audience vision impaired&lt;/a&gt;, 49% with a physical disability, and 59% with a disability of some kind, there is a high need for the process to be fully accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The applicants interviewed all used reading glasses and struggled to read the smaller text on the paper application form. If the application form is accessed as a downloadable pdf, it’s possible to enlarge the text, but the content doesn’t reflow into the screen, therefore comprehension is compromised. The downloadable pdf hasn’t been tagged with appropriate markup labels, therefore is not accessible to those using screen reader technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m partially blind, so if things are on a computer I can zoom in and read them”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of Rates Rebate is complex and the wording confusing, and full of government jargon which places cognitive load onto the applicant. There are multiple dates to remember, and applicants struggle to remember the details of previous applications. A proportion of the interviewed applicants had impaired hearing, and can struggle to comprehend the details of the process when speaking to someone on the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dexterity is impacted and a large proportion of applicants have difficulty writing their details on the form, and the process of signing their signature can be challenging and demeaning. The paper form requires the applicant to repeat a lot of the same information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Sorry, my fingers don’t work very well”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The requirement to physically present to council to sign the declaration can be impossible for people with mobility challenges without getting help from others. This is acknowledged as the most significant barrier to completion. At busy times in the rating year, the applicant will need to stand in a queue while waiting to have their application processed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Trouble is I can’t walk very far now. My knees and my ankles have packed up. I can’t drive at the moment because my shoulder’s packed”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-insight-5&quot;&gt;Key insight #5&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retirement village residents were well supported and had wrap around services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In February 2018 an amendment was made to the Rates Rebate Act to grant those who live in retirement villages eligible to receive rates rebates (in the form of a refund). This first eligible rating year has been supported by local councils, with a concerted effort to reach retirement villages in their region to give support, information and additional service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local councils have provided reach and information to residents through the support network of each village. The council staff visited retirement villages to help support and process the application, and provide the necessary additional forms. The applicants had the application forms brought to them, the supplementary rating declaration provided through the village, and the council visiting to help with enquires and witnessing signatures. This removed the need for applicants to visit their council to sign the statutory declaration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result the experience of village residents has been very positive, and for most, the first time applying for a rates rebate reimbursement. There were some examples of information getting misconstrued between villages, local council and the residents, but the applicants generally found the process straightforward and easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“For living in the village, it’s just really easy, we don’t have to remember because they come to us”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“They were very helpful, the lady that was here”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the rates paid by residents are not transparent or readily available, and applicants rely on the village administrators to supply this information to them, and to provide the authorised signatures on the supplementary information form. If the village administrators do not supply this information, then the application form cannot be processed. There were examples of applications waiting at council offices, that could not be processed because the supporting documentation from the village administrators had not been completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further research is recommended to observe the next rating year and the uptake from this segment as the local councils will not be providing the same level of promotion or visits to the villages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-insight-6&quot;&gt;Key insight #6&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a significant appetite for automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Results from surveys and interviews indicate that the majority of applicants would prefer to have the form prefilled based on their previous application. There was a significant appetite for allowing government departments to share their data and assumed this is already happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eligible ratepayers are surprised that they are required to fill in the form manually every year. This perplexes a lot of people as they find repeating the process of getting the information from separate government authorities inefficient and a waste of time. People’s circumstances don’t generally change each year, yet the same information is required every rating year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some people kept documents in a folder for easy reference, other applicants lost documentation altogether. This meant that applicants would need to contact Work and Income, Inland Revenue and banking institutions to get documentation for proof of income. There were instances of applicants receiving the wrong information or advice at this step, and either giving up or missing the application date altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dates are difficult to understand and people struggle to remember how they did the process previously. Applicants frequently reapply within the same rating year, not realising they have already applied, and turn up unnecessarily to the council. Some applicants don’t remember to apply from year to year and need to be reminded by their council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applicants will often identify as names other than what appears on the Rating Information Database, such as middle or shortened names. This can cause slow downs at council when the application is being processed. Current process with paper application requires double handling and repetition of data entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What a huge waste of low-income earners time, when we could be working to earn more money.” ONLINE SURVEY&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“I think all low-income households who have a current community services card entitlement should be able to apply without so much fuss. I currently have to fill in forms, sit and wait at a JP office and then post or physically drop all this into the council.” ONLINE SURVEY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-insight-7&quot;&gt;Key insight #7&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eligible applicants are not applying because their personal data is not private.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is some embarrassment about income and asking for any form of help which was a barrier to applying, especially in smaller communities where the applicants are likely to personally know the council staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are important cultural attitudes around receiving money and help, and during the research we found evidence of some, but believe there is more. There is currently no visibility of the people who are eligible but choose not to apply for this reason, so further research could be explored in this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there is a legal requirement for the signatures on the statutory declaration, most applicants visit council offices to process the signatures and risk having their details discussed in a public space. Additional data is gathered but not required in the legislation, and lack of clarity of process has led to inconsistent outcomes. The process is open to an individual’s interpretation of the rules, personal decisions and unconscious bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the three week Beta online trial there was an enquiry from a potential applicant who wanted to know if the council staff would be able to see their personal information. When discovering that their information would be visible to council staff, they declined to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Anyway, being a much smaller town, more often than not we know those bringing the forms in” COUNCIL STAFF MEMBER&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Whilst being appreciative some of them are also embarrassed to have to come in and feel like their financial situation is scrutinised.” COUNCIL STAFF MEMBER&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Some people may know about it but not many would share this information with each other because they don’t want to share their income or let people know they are on a low income” APPLICANT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-insight-8&quot;&gt;Key insight #8&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statutory declaration is a significant barrier to the completion of the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The current statutory declaration requires the applicant to be physically present at the council office or other stated authority to sign and witness their application. This adds financial cost of travel, stress for those with declining mobility or those who are embarrassed to apply for a benefit style payment in a smaller community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Older customers are more likely to have age onset disabilities that make it difficult for them to get out and about to be able to sign for the Rates Rebate. For those able to drive, finding parking close to council offices can be challenging, as can getting to the council during business hours. There are applicants who are unable to drive and rely on others, or incur the cost of a taxi. Some applicants need a support person with them, and need help with interpreting and understanding the process. Some are unable to walk or stand for long periods of time, housebound or hospitalised. Some applicants are the caregiver for their partner, and they need to arrange additional care for their partner, while they visit the council to sign the form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some applicants have mental health issues and can only come into Council on a ‘good day’. The good days can take some work, and add to the overall stress for applicants. Some can react and become volatile, and can put the council staff at risk. Some applicants can have high anxiety and can be too scared to leave the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Council staff often visit applicants at home to allow them to complete the process. Home visits need to accommodate for staff safety, so it takes two staff members out of the council team, and takes out the use of a council vehicle. Councils will often employ extra staff to cover this busy time, but for some councils it’s not practical to do home visits because of the spread over remote outlying areas and small staff numbers. There has been added confusion and rework with the wrong people witnessing (e.g. Real estate agents, family or non CA accountants).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The On-line process is very straightforward, however the requirement to make a declaration in front of a council officer somewhat defeats the on-line process.” ONLINE SURVEY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;statutory-declaration-council-stories&quot;&gt;Statutory declaration: Council stories&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“She got a taxi to drop her to our offices, she got halfway through the doors and needed a chair to rest to catch her breath and rest her legs. Then she made it inside to the counter and sat down while I went through her rebate with her. Then I had to escort her to our cashiers (stopping midway to sit and rest) so she could get some cash out and order her taxi home. It was a big ordeal for her which had her in tears.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“He has a head injury and is very volatile. It depends on the day as to what response you will get when you do a home visit. It takes two staff members to visit him and sometimes he won’t let them in!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“She is bed bound, not just housebound - so the staff have to go in to her bedroom every year. She has to arrange for her home helper to be there when the staff come so it takes a bit of arranging for her and I am sure it is quite intrusive having administration staff from her local Council in her bedroom.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“She is housebound and asks family members who need to coordinate the visit so they can be at the house and explain things to the ratepayer and just be there for reassurance. Often the ratepayer doesn’t really understand what is going on and the disruption to their normal routine and having strangers in their home is very upsetting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“He is schizophrenic and doesn’t like people so won’t come into the Council building. Staff phone his caregiver and arrange a time and she drives him to the car park and staff go out and witness his signature in the car park.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“She has 6 young with children with medical conditions. It is extremely difficult for her to organise the time to come into the Council to have her application witnessed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The elderly are very susceptible to winter illnesses, and yet they often come out of their sick beds and warm houses to sign.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-insight-9&quot;&gt;Key insight #9&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-9&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a need for human contact and support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is a need for the applicants to be able to talk to someone for help, even if the system is automated. Most applicants are comfortable using the phone to make an enquiry, and will use often talk to someone to understand how to navigate the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customers often call Council or Citizens Advice Bureau to ask ‘How do I start?’. They want to talk to someone to understand clearly and easily what they need to do. People who are really marginalised and needing help often just need to talk to someone in person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A complex system can be better delivered as an automated process, however automation can also bring gaps and oversights in the system. This can lead to individuals dropping out of the system. Our research surfaced an example of an individual who missed getting a Community Service Card because of an error made through the IRD system miscalculating income. This meant eligibility for other services and support was denied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the bulk of Rates Rebate applications can be processed with an automated approach, there is still a need for the system to build in human effort for the edge cases or enquiries. The skills of the service centres can adequately provide customers with the support they need. In this way the process can prioritise meaningful human interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the council service centres is in the process of installing kiosks to support those customers wishing to self serve a transaction. A concierge service directs people to the service they require, and can answer their questions. If they are there for an enquiry they can go talk to one of the staff. If they really want a human to do their transaction for them that’s ok too, they may just need to stand in a queue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of the group have heard about Rates Rebate from friends and family, or through their local council. Applicants often get help from their family, support networks or from council staff to help fill in the form. There are some applicants who enjoy the interaction with the council, and will make an occasion of it, dress up and make a day of it. They enjoy the process if it is a positive one, but get very frustrated if they get the wrong information or need to wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Talking to someone about it - so that made me happy”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-insight-10&quot;&gt;Key insight #10&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-10&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently bereaved need additional help with the application process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Recently bereaved applicants struggle to cope with taking over the household administration if they have not done it previously. Some applicants can find the process daunting and overwhelming in addition to the other tasks left to them to manage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common scenario is that the applicant has had to care and support their unwell partner, and then is left to cope with the burden of taking over all the household administration tasks. This is also impacted by the grief and upheaval of the considerable change in their life situation. The deceased partner is likely to have previously managed all the finances, household structure and rates administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applicants can be confused when trying to apply on their own, but don’t want to take up others time and be a burden. While they are trying to do their best, they struggle to know where to start. There are genuine attempts to comprehend what is needed but they get confused in the process, and need to be supported through the process. Often they will need to learn to drive and will need to gain the confidence to travel independently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“She is a recently widowed lady whose husband used to deal with the rebates and such like. She is not a well woman and rarely leaves the house. She gets quite overwhelmed if she has to deal with bureaucracy so we visit to make it easier for her.” COUNCIL STAFF MEMBER&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“She came into the offices for her rebate appointment. Her husband had just passed away and she needed the rebate to continue to live in the property. She cried throughout the appointment and was very embarrassed. Her husband did all the finances and she was now having to learn to cope with everything and to pay for everything herself.” COUNCIL STAFF MEMBER&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“She’s never filled out the application form. Her husband’s always done it” COUNCIL INTERPRETER&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-insight-11&quot;&gt;Key insight #11&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-KeyInsight-11&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leverage the best channels for awareness and support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the biggest barriers to applying is that ratepayers don’t know about Rates Rebates and that they may be eligible. Various channels used by this audience can be leveraged to raise awareness and support the application process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research identified common groups, organisations and entities that could be used to support information, communication and other assistance for these customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending time with friends and family rated highly, and we also learned that social groups are already are the most common way that people hear about Rates Rebate. Council and Libraries were also identified as effective channels for reaching the target audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also an opportunity to raise awareness through commonly used Gold Card and Community Services Card channels, and during interactions with health professionals and doctors, in local practices and hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supermarket shopping is a common and frequent activity and may offer additional reach through supplementary advertising. IRD interaction is less frequent, but common across all ratepayers so could offer reminders or additional information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good proportion of this audience can be reached online through various approaches, especially leveraging social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Certainly everyone had heard about it here, and I think it was like a little bushfire that went through” RETIREMENT VILLAGE RESIDENT&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“I’ve got to go to the doctor on Friday. Last year I was often at the hospital” PRIVATE HOME RESIDENT&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Skype and Facepage. Because we talk to Adelaide quite often, and England of course” RETIREMENT VILLAGE RESIDENT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information and frequency of interactions are available in the &lt;em&gt;Appendix&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix-1-&quot;&gt;Appendix #1 &lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-AutomationFeedback&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;automation-feedback&quot;&gt;Automation feedback&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following questions about automation were asked via two online surveys, and during the face to face interviews with applicants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;permission-to-prefill-the-application-form&quot;&gt;Permission to prefill the application form&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pie Chart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“And they all moaned because they thought they should just get it and not have to fill it out every year”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Reams of stuff to fill in”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;permission-to-share-information-from-other-government-agencies&quot;&gt;Permission to share information from other government agencies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pie Chart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You should know what it is”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“The rates office knows all the answers really. They know what we pay and they know what the village pays, so why don’t they just fill it in and I’ll just sign it”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;permission-to-share-information-from-other-government-agencies-1&quot;&gt;Permission to share information from other government agencies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was less interest in sharing information from government agencies, than having the form automatically prefilled based on the previous years application. Some of the reasons why applicants chose ‘No’ to this option were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Previous system errors with agencies had impacted their eligibility for other entitlements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Didn’t understand how Ministry Social Development were relevant to them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Couldn’t understand how this could be automated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Didn’t think Inland Revenue was relevant because they didn’t earn any income&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Had an accountant so didn’t need input from Inland Revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pie Chart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix-2&quot;&gt;Appendix #2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;completing-the-paper-application-form&quot;&gt;Completing the paper application form&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-CompletingPaperForm&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the interview process we observed the nine applicants filling in the 2018/2019 Rates Rebate paper application form. We asked them to talk about what they found challenging as they were going through the process. Overall, applicants found the size of the text too small and difficult to read. A lot of information and instruction was skim read but not absorbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-4.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Application Form&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;name-a&quot;&gt;Name (A)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First name / Last name fields were often transposed. People automatically wrote their first name in the Last Name field.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Title was often overlooked&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some were unsure as to which name to use, as they were known by their middle name, or a variation of their name. These names would be different to what the ‘official’ name stated on the Rating Information Database (RID).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;address-b&quot;&gt;Address (B)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People would start to write their whole address in the first field, then get confused at what they should write in Suburb/Town and postal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A lot of people knew their postcode&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A lot of people had an email address&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People were often confused when filling out the question ‘Did you move here from another property during the rating year? If they selected ‘No’, they didn’t realise they could skip the next question ‘If yes, on what date did you settle the sale of your previous property for this rating year?’. They would try and fill out the next questions and get very confused. It would take them a while to figure out that they could have skipped those questions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Retirement village residents sometimes have their own individual street address (number and street name) within the retirement village, but most assumed they could just use the format they would use as a postal address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dependants-c&quot;&gt;Dependants (C)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This question wasn’t relevant for the group we interviewed. They either wrote N/A or put a line through the boxes. However, this information is not legally required by the Act, and its possible that this question may add a barrier to completion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;income-declaration-d&quot;&gt;Income Declaration (D)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People skim read the instructions, filled in the tick box (New Zealand Superannuation) and then wrote ‘Retired’ in the Occupation field. This is a duplicate of information as there is a NZ Superannuation $ field below, and an addition ‘Occupation’ question on the Stat Dec page. Ideally the repetition could be removed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The format of the ‘Source of income’ fields worked well and there were no issues with understanding where to put the $ amounts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The problem with the income information was that a lot of the applicants didn’t understand that the requirement is for Gross income rather than Net income. People would either guess the amount, or look at their bank account to see what comes in every week/fortnight and do some complex maths to estimate what that would be over a year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was confusion over the difference between NZ Superannuation and Personal Superannuation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-5.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Application Form&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rates-e&quot;&gt;Rates (E)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most people guessed their rates or left the field blank for the council to fill in.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People were uncertain of the different types of rates (local, regional, water)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;important-information-f&quot;&gt;Important Information (F)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This was skim read by the applicants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;declaration-g&quot;&gt;Declaration (G)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Name, Address and Occupation fields are all double up from previous parts of the form. Is there a way to structure this so this data is only written once?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Declared at’ caused confusion for a lot of people, as they started to write the date in this field. When they realised their mistake they weren’t sure what the term meant. Most eventually guessed it as ‘place’, but didn’t realise that this was for the authorised witness to fill in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;calculation-table-h&quot;&gt;Calculation table (H)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This table was often overlooked, but when prompted the applicants found it easy to interpret. Retirement village residents don’t have access to their rates amounts, so are unable to use this table.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-6.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Application Form&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix-3&quot;&gt;Appendix #3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frequently-used-channels&quot;&gt;Frequently used channels&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-FrequentlyUsedChannels&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest barriers to applying is that ratepayers don’t know about Rates Rebates and that they may be eligible. As part of our research we asked questions to inform how we might better raise awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the research surfaced common groups, organisations and entities that could be used to support information, communication and other assistance for these customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-keeps-you-busy&quot;&gt;What keeps you busy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-7.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Application Form&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These channels have been grouped into three sections; ‘Often’, ‘Sometimes’ and ‘Rarely’ to describe the general frequency of interaction with these groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frequency-often&quot;&gt;Frequency: Often&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-8.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Application Form&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frequency-sometimes&quot;&gt;Frequency: Sometimes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-9.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-9.png&quot; alt=&quot;Application Form&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frequency-rarely&quot;&gt;Frequency: Rarely&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-10.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR-Beta-Research-Report-10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Application Form&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>karyn-brice</name></author><category term="rates rebate" /><summary type="html">This report presents the findings of a rapid research project which was part of the Beta phase of the Rates Rebate project.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Service Innovation Lab - Using Kumu to share our research</title><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/10/Using-Kumu-To-Share-Our-Research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Service Innovation Lab - Using Kumu to share our research" /><published>2019-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/10/Using-Kumu-To-Share-Our-Research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/10/Using-Kumu-To-Share-Our-Research/">&lt;p&gt;The Service Innovation Lab  often undertakes design research into topics that impact multiple agencies and the teams within them. That means it’s important to share our learnings in a way that supports a number of work streams and potentially reduces the need for repeat user research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;testing-ways-to-share-our-findings&quot;&gt;Testing ways to share our findings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many other people are interested in the specific topic/s associated with our work, such as accessing services, identity and privacy concerns, our project team thought the Becoming an Adult project would be a good scenario to test a different way to share our findings.
The usual outcome of our research would be a report and/or presentation; this provides a highly curated view of the data relevant to our project objectives. Furthermore, in the process of doing field research you often learn a bunch of things not specifically related to the project objectives — but this data might be useful to others.
This prototype looked at how to share the collected data with others to assess its connection and usefulness to their work. This involved digitising all the data we found compelling from our transcripts, even where it didn’t have a direct link to our key insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;visual-presentation&quot;&gt;Visual presentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We met potential consumers of this data and realised it would be useful to present our findings visually. The goal was to provide an at-a-glance view of any data in our transcripts and enabling potential consumers to easily and quickly search or identify topics of interest.
This would enable other project teams to not only decide if there was relevant data but understand our logic — from insight to verbatim quotes that could then be referenced in transcripts for full context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;combining-kumu-with-google-sheets&quot;&gt;Combining Kumu with Google Sheets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool we chose to test this idea was Kumu . However, we didn’t want to be bound to a particular tool, so we chose to create a database using Google Sheets that could be tested with other tools.
Combining Kumu with the Google Sheets app dramatically sped up the process of data entry and validation, as both apps could be accessed and updated by multiple users simultaneously. This enabled quick updating and version history of the data and visualisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;digitising-the-data&quot;&gt;Digitising the data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We estimate it took two team members a day and a half to enter all the data from post-it notes into spreadsheet format, ready to be imported into Kumu. At this point the data in Kumu reflected what we had analysed as a team and posted on the wall.
From here, time was spent familiarising ourselves with Kumu and how we could further synthesise and arrange the data beyond what’s viable with post-its. This is when we really started to notice the power of Kumu to highlight areas in our data that needed attention and when data entry errors were corrected.
We re-drew how we wanted the data to be organised, and revised hierarchies on a whiteboard to help inform data cleaning and create a less confusing visual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;presenting-data-in-a-shareable-and-reusable-format&quot;&gt;Presenting data in a shareable and reusable format&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, this process felt faster to get to a shareable and reusable format for our target users (researchers and designers). The process of digitising and recreating the synthesis also added extra rigor to our analysis as it was an opportunity to question how we categorised and interpreted the raw data.
Kumu enabled the data to be more intricately connected using tags and connections, reflecting a realistic complexity to what we learnt and made the often abstract process of analysis and synthesis more tangible.
When we shared this, there was excitement at seeing this type of data presented in such a way and initial reviews are that it feels intuitive, and “certainly a lot easier to go through than other data sets I’ve been given.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;becoming-an-adult-data-in-kumu-demo&quot;&gt;Becoming an Adult data in Kumu demo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nG3EQd686Pc&quot; title=&quot;Becoming an adult data in Kumu demo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;This video shows how Kumu was used to visualise the qualitative data collected as part of the Becoming an Adult research discovery. This was an experiment in sharing research across teams designing and developing identity services in government.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or would like to know more about Kumu or insights from the Becoming an Adult project, please contact the Service Innovation Lab&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Service Innovation is part of the Department of Internal Affairs. It’s charged with working collaboratively across agencies to centre government services around the needs of people.  You’ll find us either at ‘the Lab’ on Thorndon Quay or Level 10, 45 Pipitea St in Wellington.
If you’d like to stay across the work coming out of the Lab &lt;a href=&quot;https://confirmsubscription.com/h/j/7AA94B673345A7D5&quot;&gt;join our mailing list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>matthew-mccallum</name></author><category term="better public services" /></entry><entry><title type="html">ACC Better Rules Collaboration report summary</title><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/01/ACC-Better-Rules-Collaboration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ACC Better Rules Collaboration report summary" /><published>2019-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/01/ACC-Better-Rules-Collaboration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/07/01/ACC-Better-Rules-Collaboration/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/Exploring_Machine_Consumable_Code_With_ACC.pdf&quot;&gt;Exploring Machine Consumable Code - ACC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supported by the Accident Compensation Corporation (‘ACC’), the Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment (‘MBIE’) is exploring ways to modernise the Accident Compensation Act 2001 (‘the AC Act’). This includes exploring a structural rewrite to provide a modern and responsive piece of legislation that supports effective and efficient delivery of the accident compensation scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While exploring opportunities to make the AC Act more accessible and fit for purpose from a structural rewrite, MBIE and ACC learned about ‘machine consumable’ legislation, and the work of the ‘better rules – better outcomes’ (‘Better Rules’) initiative and the Service Innovation Lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine consumable legislation means that its rules can be presented in a structured format (code) that can be processed by a machine (computer) without human intervention. It recognises that machines are ubiquitous, services are increasingly consumed digitally, and there are many uses for machine consumable legislation that are only beginning to be explored. The Better Rules initiative is examining ways to support this through the way New Zealand regulation is developed and implemented, and the Service Innovation Lab previously facilitated a similar experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;approach&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cross-agency and multidisciplinary Accident Compensation Better Rules Discovery Team (‘the team’) undertook a ‘discovery’ (experiment) over six weeks of half-days based at the Service Innovation Lab starting March 2019. The team comprised legal, policy, legal drafting, business rules, operational, and software development experts from ACC, MBIE, the Parliamentary Counsel Office, the Department of Internal Affairs (‘Internal Affairs’), the Inland Revenue Department (‘Inland Revenue’), and the Service Innovation Lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery aimed to develop a blueprint of rules for entitlements in the AC Act by developing concept models, decision models, rules statements, and code. The discovery was to support a potential structural rewrite of the AC Act through: creating a shared understanding of the rules for entitlements; exploring use of machines to identify gaps in logic of the rules; providing a practical example that shows how this approach can be applied; and developing tools and techniques that could be applied to future work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team recognised that it was unrealistic to complete this blueprint for all entitlements in this time, and developed a prioritised list of entitlements to work through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-findings&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key findings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rules statements are of significant value for legal drafters&lt;/strong&gt;: Rules statements – a simple set of rules synthesised from complex legislation – that have been robustly developed and tested are expected to assist the Parliamentary Counsel Office (legal drafters) to undertake a more comprehensive and accurate rewrite that is more human and machine consumable.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing rules statements identified gaps&lt;/strong&gt;: The process of developing rules statements identified gaps in the logic of legislation that had not been previously identified, which range from technical gaps that could be resolved by legal drafters through to gaps that require further analysis. By resolving these logic gaps, legislation can be more human and machine consumable, the risk of misinterpretation can be reduced, and what is implemented can better match policy intent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Legislation may have longer rules and more of them&lt;/strong&gt;: A prevailing view in the team at the beginning of the discovery was that a structural rewrite would result in fewer or shorter rules to make the AC Act more accessible and human consumable. To the contrary, the team found that ensuring there are no gaps in the rule logic can result in longer rules. However, these longer rules were clearer and would ensure legislation is more human and machine consumable. Furthermore, as legislation becomes machine consumable, and policy developers have tools to better understand and model its (positive and negative) effects, additional rules may be created to create more nuanced policy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing rules statements and code at the same time most effective&lt;/strong&gt;: The discovery initially explored handing rules statements to software developers for turning into code. However, it was found that writing code at the same time as rules statements produced better quality rules statements and code, and was more efficient. It improved shared understanding, reduced follow up questions, and allowed the code to validate the rules statements.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concept models improved shared understanding&lt;/strong&gt;: The use of concept models as the first step for any new topic improved shared understanding and team engagement. They showed not only what was in scope but also what was out and enabled focused and effective communication. Concept models proved to be a core first step for the multi-disciplinary team to start working on each entitlement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A small multidisciplinary team can produce most outputs&lt;/strong&gt;: While the discovery had a broader team to draw on (and who were all used), the outputs that would support a structural rewrite were produced with a small team (fewer than six) of experts across business rules, operations, policy, legal, legal drafters, and software development.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tools increased efficiency and broadened use of code&lt;/strong&gt;: During the discovery, the team identified areas where different tools may have been of value, including tools for capturing concept models, tools that can test policy, and tools for storing rules in a dataset form from which executable legislation as code could be derived. The team experimented with tools and found that they demonstrated value and (at least in one case) were complementary to each other, but neither is necessary for a structural rewrite alone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rules requiring human judgement can be written in code&lt;/strong&gt;: The team explored developing code for an area of legislation requiring significant human judgement to test whether it is difficult to code, and found it was no different or more complex than other rules. It emerged that identifying these types of rules could be used to track the quantity of human judgement within a piece of legislation, which could provide a new perspective and way to measure how much a piece of legislation introduces.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Value of software developers is beyond code&lt;/strong&gt;: The software developers brought a lot of value to the multi-disciplinary team that was beyond the code they create. They looked at rules and logic on behalf of the machine, and improved the logic and robustness of rules statements.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A multidisciplinary team improves implementation&lt;/strong&gt;: Using a multidisciplinary team to develop rules statements improved connections of people involved in policy development through to those in operations, and was observed to reduce translation gaps and is expected to improve implementation. It also sped up the cadence of work as the experts were in the room at the right time, eliminating handover errors and delays that usually occur when experts from a different team provide input.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;opportunities&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opportunities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop rules statements for other parts of the AC Act&lt;/strong&gt;: To support legal drafters to ensure a structural rewrite would result in more human and machine consumable legislation, MBIE and ACC should develop rules statements for all provisions in the AC Act that may benefit from this work. A pragmatic approach would be to develop a prioritised list of provisions that would benefit most from rules statements, and scope the effort (time and resources) to complete that work in the time available. This does not require another intensive discovery, but rather could use regular discrete blocks of time (eg, 4 hours per week over six months). To develop code that tests the logic, a software developer is required.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use methods from the discovery for other policy and legislative changes&lt;/strong&gt;: While the focus has been on a structural rewrite, the approach tested across the six-week discovery could also be used as part of everyday business when considering policy and legislative changes. While this is particularly true for the AC Act, which is complex and composed of many interrelated provisions, considering different policy and legislative proposals against rules statements and code would robustly test their logic and implications.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improve macro view through concept models&lt;/strong&gt;: MBIE and ACC should seek opportunities to improve the macro view of accident compensation scheme settings through concept models. This could give a transparent and consistent view of the accident compensation scheme, and provide a common foundation for cross-agency collaboration, in the same way the smaller and more targeted concept models did for the discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code the whole AC Act and make it public&lt;/strong&gt;: To fully support the long-term ambition of machine consumable legislation in New Zealand, ACC, MBIE, the Better Rules initiative, and the Service Innovation Lab could explore coding the whole AC Act. Much of the AC Act would have been coded as part of the process of creating the rules statements. A key realisation of the potential of machine consumable legislation is publicly publishing the code in an executable form for the same reasoning governments publish their legislative text: to aid people’s comprehension of the law. Coding the AC Act would be dependent on the Better Rules initiative completing its planned work on developing New Zealand standards and architecture for machine consumable legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continue to explore using code already developed&lt;/strong&gt;: Some code has already been developed as part of the process to develop rules statements (and more would be developed if the rules statements are developed). This code presents a unique opportunity for innovation. For example, it could be used for policy development (eg, modelling test cases), for consumers or advocates to develop an end-user interface, or for government to see how the accident compensation legislation interacts with other legislation. Working with the Better Rules initiative and the Service Innovation Lab, ACC and MBIE should continue to explore this so that the opportunity is not wasted.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full report about this discovery is &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/Exploring_Machine_Consumable_Code_With_ACC.pdf&quot;&gt;available as a PDF&lt;/a&gt;; however we are currently working on an accessible version of this for future release. As always we would like to know your thoughts and comments about the Better Rules work so please &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;make contact with us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>glen-thurston</name></author><category term="better rules" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Service Innovation Lab - Shaping government services around entry to adulthood</title><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/06/12/Becoming-An-Adult/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Service Innovation Lab - Shaping government services around entry to adulthood" /><published>2019-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/06/12/Becoming-An-Adult</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/06/12/Becoming-An-Adult/">&lt;p&gt;Becoming an adult is a key time when people begin to interact with government in new ways as they make significant decisions about their lives. During this period, young adults are not only defining who they are and what they care about, but they may also be entering tertiary study or further training, becoming a parent, getting a job, leaving home, moving to another region or going overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Becoming an adult in New Zealand looks very different for each person and can be influenced by many variables. The ‘becoming an adult’ project was undertaken by a cross-branch DIA team to look into improving how young adults access government services and prove who they are (manage their identity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-objectives&quot;&gt;Project objectives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand the current state of identity management for 16-20 year olds and the role digital identity currently has in their lives.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test assumptions around the experience, use of and value of digital identity for accessing government services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify opportunities and future trends that could support this cohort in accessing services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-approach&quot;&gt;Our approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project was the first chance for the whole design team at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io/&quot;&gt;Service Innovation Lab&lt;/a&gt; to work together to not only achieve the brief faster but consolidate our approach on how we run research discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of this was to test our new measurement framework to better understand what good work looks like at a project level. For more detail read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/what-does-good-look-like/&quot;&gt;What Does ‘Good’ Look Like? Innovation in Public Service Design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project team comprises a product owner, 4 service designers and a scrum master, and the work was undertaken over 12 weeks.
With a limited timeframe to complete the research the team used the following approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Semi-structured interviews 1.5 hours long with tailored activities around control and independence, identity and online behaviour.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Desk research on emerging trends, literature review and analysis, and testing of existing services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connected with identity experts and projects across government.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help guide our interviews from broad to narrow areas of interest we designed a series of activities and tools. In particular, we wanted to deep dive into what control/independence looked like to young adults as well as how they gained and used various types of attributes and information about themselves online and in person.
The tools were designed to make it easy to translate the findings into quantifiable data to identify patterns across our cohort. Alongside these activities we asked about online behaviour, privacy concerns, plans and aspirations.
The other benefit of using tools and activities was to give consistency in the quality and type of data collected, as the interviews were being conducted by a larger team with different levels of experience and confidence with this type of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-we-met&quot;&gt;Who we met&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team interviewed 10 young adults aged 16 to 21. They were carefully recruited to give us a diverse set of perspectives over a demographic representation.
The group contained a range of ethnic, refugee and migrant backgrounds: a mix of rural, urban and living away from home as well as high and low decile schooling. The team decided longer interviews with less people was the right balance to meet our objectives and identify patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-we-learnt&quot;&gt;What we learnt&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even from our small sample we managed to collect a wealth of data that could be used to inform actionable insights and challenge a bunch of assumptions. The tools performed well both in the field and during analysis of the data. We also validated our findings against academic studies and research being undertaken by a variety of organisations in New Zealand and abroad to build a bigger picture of where the young adults we spoke to fit in at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;influences&quot;&gt;Influences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their transition to adulthood, young people are defining their identity; who they are as individuals and what they care about, support or believe. Many were struggling to manage the pressures and influences put on them by parents, peers, family and even themselves. Some were compromising doing something they were passionate about for something that would get them employment, financial stability or would allow them to travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;responsibility&quot;&gt;Responsibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research by Massey University on the topic reveals young adults today aren’t taking on the adult roles and responsibilities in the way previous generations had. While they are legally able to do many tasks on their own, most got help from parents and siblings to access services, such as applying for government support and passports.
This made it difficult to understand pain-points as young adults might not be experiencing them directly because others were doing this for them, or they were not doing it frequently enough to remember. For example, when asked about applying for their driver’s licence many could tell us in detail about the test and studying for it, yet none were sure about completing the application process. Their guardians were often left looking after their “serious” or “important” identity documents even after the person had left home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;technology-use&quot;&gt;Technology use&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were very surprised at their attitude toward technology. Most said they used it frequently, yet there was a real awareness of the negative impact it can have on their lives. Clear distinctions were made between using it for something productive or educational — or for recreation, such as social media. Some even went so far as to monitor the time they spent on their phone and were actively trying to reduce it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;identity-in-visuals&quot;&gt;Identity in visuals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following diagrams visualise when young adults are creating new IDs and which IDs are most used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Becoming-An-Adult/idcreation2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Becoming-An-Adult/idcreation2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ID timeline: creation by age&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The diagram is a horizontal line with birth at the left end and turning 21 at the right end. The line is punctuated by dots indicating when IDs are acquired and the size of the dot grows based on how many of our cohort were included. The diagram reveals that all had birth certificates and only a few acquired IDs between their childhood and the age of 13 where the majority of ID activity occurs until about 17 years old followed by a minor amount into early 20s.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This diagram shows our 10 young adults all had birth certificates and later between 13 and 17 years old acquired many other IDs, such as driver’s licences and online accounts, such as Google and Facebook. The diagram below shows the strong use of online IDs and large ownership of government issued IDs. Note that we included a wide range of items that might not technically be considered forms of identity but this was to understand young adults perception and awareness of government issued documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/media/Becoming-An-Adult/idownership2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Becoming-An-Adult/idownership2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ID ownership vs usage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;This diagram uses 2 axes, ownership and usage, to plot various types of identity documents and cards young adults had in their wallet or at home. We used this diagram to understand what was the most commonly owned and most used forms of ID. The key insights from this graph is that bank cards, student IDs, Facebook and Google accounts made up the most owned and used followed closely by drivers licence. The least used and owned IDs were Kiwi Access card and firearms licence. There was a cluster of IDs that many people owned but didn’t frequently use which was made up of many government issued IDs such as birth certificate, passport, IRD number and national student number.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full information on the insights gathered in the Becoming an Adult project can be made available so get in touch.  We’ll publish another blog post soon on how we’re exploring ways to share user research. If you’d like to stay across the work coming out of the Lab &lt;a href=&quot;https://confirmsubscription.com/h/j/7AA94B673345A7D5&quot;&gt;join our mailing list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>matthew-mccallum</name></author><category term="agency engagement" /><category term="blog post" /><category term="digital identity" /><category term="government services" /><category term="life events" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Renting a Property - Continuing our discovery</title><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/01/30/renting-a-property-continuing-our-discovery/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Renting a Property - Continuing our discovery" /><published>2019-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/01/30/renting-a-property-continuing-our-discovery</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/01/30/renting-a-property-continuing-our-discovery/">&lt;p&gt;In July and August 2018, a small team from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mbie.govt.nz/business-and-employment/business/support-for-business/better-for-business/about-better-for-business/&quot;&gt;Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment (MBIE)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://msd.govt.nz/&quot;&gt;Ministry of Social Development  (MSD)&lt;/a&gt; and the Service Innovation Lab from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dia.govt.nz/&quot;&gt;Department of Internal Affairs  (DIA)&lt;/a&gt;, continued our discovery into &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/renting-a-property-understanding-how-better-relationships-support-better-rentals/&quot;&gt;Renting a Property&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase two of the discovery took place over four weeks. The core team received support from subject matter experts (SME) across government agencies. The team did a detailed analysis of the findings from the first discovery and collected new information from SMEs to validate the problems and next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;validation&quot;&gt;Validation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to enter the design phase where we can design, build, test and learn, we needed to understand the following from discovery research:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the problem?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who is it a problem for?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When is it happening?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would likely fail to have any impact unless we identify the “who, what and when” before we start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discovered in phase one of our research that there are complex relationship dynamics associated with renting. The relationships are person to person, and also between people and property. Next, we defined each type of relationship, how it works, and what makes a relationship good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good relationship can include the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Issues are raised without fear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Issues are resolved in a timely manner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rapport - (know names, situation etc)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consideration of actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Going above and beyond requirements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taking pride in their house and responsibilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Autonomy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maintain the mana and integrity of the other person or persons in the relationship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We noted that defined responsibilities and expectations are important to reducing conflict or managing it when it arises through accountability. Similarly, transparency encourages fairness and equality, and manages the expectations of both parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-outcomes&quot;&gt;The outcomes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the analysis and validation we identified these key insights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is strong evidence that the barriers to a ‘quality relationship’ between the parties to a tenancy start before the actual tenancy commences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is an opportunity to be pre-emptive as it is the time before a tenancy starts in which the relationship between landlords and tenant is most critical. The events of this time have a long term impact throughout renting life journey.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is strong evidence that removing known barriers at the beginning of the renting relationship can reduce the likelihood of issues and conflict arising during a tenancy and increases a quick resolution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on these insights, two key issues stand out. Both these issues occur before people start renting a property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Securing a property to rent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forming a tenancy agreement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identified segments of people that are struggling to acquire a rental property. This could be for a variety of reasons, but we think it would be an ideal cohort to work with as there is an excellent opportunity to achieve collective impact by applying a cross-agency approach with these groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-informed-these-outcomes&quot;&gt;What informed these outcomes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defining and mapping the 31 unique tenancy relationships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Barriers to good relationships definitions and mapping&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Landlord and Tenant Audiences - Segmentation, Archetypes, Personas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Landlord and Tenant journey and barriers maps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quantitative data analysis of discovery phase relationship findings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Logic mapping of the seven concepts from Phase One for validation against project goals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Māori concept of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/kainga-and-renting-a-property/&quot;&gt;Kāinga&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-we-used-the-research&quot;&gt;How we used the research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MBIE Tenancy Services have used this work for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design and development of a possible Tenancy Agreement Builder – direct outcome/concept from the discovery, supported by the evidence gathered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tenancy Bond Strategy – informing further research into the strategic role and direction of Tenancy Bond&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Healthy Homes Standards campaign strategy – feeding into research for the strategic direction of public engagement with the Healthy Homes Standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiple stakeholder engagement strategies with various audiences (e.g. Property Managers; Māori; etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Looking into the viability of setting up online training modules that support Tenants, Landlords and Property Managers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A primer for new staff, and to raise awareness of the importance of relationships, behaviour change, tenant fear and other problems in the market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all who participated, especially those who were interviewed, came into the Lab to help us on our journey, or took the time to give feedback on what we found and our ideas for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the size of the report, a full copy of the report is available upon request. If you’d like to stay across any of the work coming out of the Lab, please join our &lt;a href=&quot;https://confirmsubscription.com/h/j/7AA94B673345A7D5&quot;&gt;mailing list&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>glen-thurston</name></author><category term="discovery" /><category term="renting a property" /><category term="collaboration" /><summary type="html">Phase two of the discovery took place over four weeks in July and August 2018 and like the first one the core team were supported by a number of subject matter experts (SME) across government agencies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Renting a Property - Understanding how better relationships support better rentals</title><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/01/28/renting-a-property-understanding-how-better-relationships-support-better-rentals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Renting a Property - Understanding how better relationships support better rentals" /><published>2019-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/01/28/renting-a-property-understanding-how-better-relationships-support-better-rentals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2019/01/28/renting-a-property-understanding-how-better-relationships-support-better-rentals/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-of-the-research-report&quot;&gt;Summary of the research report&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2018, a small team from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mbie.govt.nz/business-and-employment/business/support-for-business/better-for-business/about-better-for-business/&quot;&gt;Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment (MBIE)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hnzc.co.nz/&quot;&gt;Housing New Zealand  (HNZ)&lt;/a&gt; and the Service Innovation Lab from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dia.govt.nz/&quot;&gt;Department of Internal Affairs  (DIA)&lt;/a&gt;, ran a five week discovery that explored landlord-tenant relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-this-topic&quot;&gt;Why this topic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At December 2017 there were 1.9 million private dwellings for 4.9 million New Zealanders. Of these, 588,700 (37% of total dwellings) were private rental households, and made up the majority of rental houses.
The proportion of New Zealanders renting increased from 23% in 1991 to 33% in 2016. In addition, people are renting for more of their lives, or permanently. Māori, Pacific peoples, and families with children are over-represented in renting statistics, while people are increasingly renting in retirement.
Housing not only fulfils the basic human need for shelter but also satisfies social requirements. A house provides a centre for an individual and the basis for family life, emerging as an important symbol of social standing and aspiration. Meeting housing needs is therefore complex.
Many rentals don’t support their occupants well when compared with owner-occupied houses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;31% of rental houses feel damp, compared to 11% of owner- occupied houses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;22% of rental homes have no fixed heating sources&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;56% of rental homes had visible mould, compared to 44% of owner-occupied houses&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of rental accomodation led the Service Innovation governance group, which MBIE belongs to, to prioritise ‘Renting a Property’as a life event to explore from a holistic, all-of-government perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-we-do-it&quot;&gt;How did we do it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our initial design statement was based on a hypothesis that a better rental house will result in a better relationship between tenant and landlord. The aim was to find out more about these relationships and the house itself. We essentially began with a fact finding mission as a foundation for future work.
Significant research had already been undertaken. We built on this, reviewing over 48 documents that provided insights into renting from landlord, property manager and tenant perspectives and conducted in-depth interviews with 60 stakeholders. We also explored wellbeing frameworks relevant to renting, including the Māori concept of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/kainga-and-renting-a-property/&quot;&gt;Kāinga&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-we-learn&quot;&gt;What did we learn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We validated our original design statement by the end of week three, but with a twist. It was actually better relationships that influence the quality of the homes. Tenants who had good relationships were less likely to go into dispute with their landlords, more likely to raise issues, and see improvements, thus increasing house quality. As a result we revised our design statement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For tenants and landlords renting a property, create ways to raise recognition that better relationships between them aid in quality rental homes which will help lead to better outcomes for both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key themes and patterns of behaviour to explore further:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relationships and communication&lt;/strong&gt; - Good relationships are essential to trust and transparency. This enables all parties to better understand each other, and make it more likely to facilitate ways to help each other. As a result, all parties had higher chances of securing tenure, trusting one another in the longer-term and improving rental stock.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rental culture&lt;/strong&gt; - Tenants, landlords and property managers said increased challenges in the rental market has caused a dysfunctional culture. Tenants worried about being “kicked out”. Some landlords and tenants faced discrimination and public stigma, which in turn led to shame for owning a rental property, or decrease their chances of finding somewhere to live.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Housing is a human right&lt;/strong&gt; - Tenants frequently experience difficulty in finding a home, with some sacrificing their resources, and some families in desperate need; many face the challenge of proving their worth as a “good” tenant and although some were determined, others felt vulnerable, judged, and unheard. Housing is a human right that some New Zealanders are excluded from.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poor and learnt behaviour&lt;/strong&gt; - There were enough stories to indicate a lack of rental knowledge, training and experience in renting was low or immature for many of the players. Poor and learnt behaviour has damaged public perceptions of these groups.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The basics are essential to living&lt;/strong&gt; - Tenants, landlords and property managers expressed the importance of having the essentials (including social and community networks) close by rentals to meet basic daily needs of tenants. Many tenants were either unable to access or were unaware of tenancy support services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a short term discovery, it wasn’t possible to tackle all the themes and problems, so two were selected to investigate further by looking at the causes and coming up with ideas to mitigate them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Security of tenure of a home for a period of time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many landlords and property managers have a lack of experience around tenancy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here we identified several high level ideas to show what future interventions might be. Due to limited time, each of these ideas and the evidence that supports them, will need to be validated in more detail to ascertain the true value of progressing this work further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-our-research&quot;&gt;Using our research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our partners, MBIE Tenancy Services, have used this work for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design and development of a possible Tenancy Agreement Builder – direct outcome/concept from the discovery, supported by the evidence gathered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tenancy Bond Strategy – informing further research into the strategic role and direction of Tenancy Bond&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Healthy Homes Standards campaign strategy – feeding into research for the strategic direction of public engagement with the Healthy Homes Standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiple stakeholder engagement strategies with various audiences (e.g. Property Managers; Māori; etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Looking into the viability of setting up online training modules that support Tenants, Landlords and Property Managers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A primer for new staff, and to raise awareness of the importance of relationships, behaviour change, tenant fear and other problems in the market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all who participated, especially those who were interviewed, came into the Lab to help us on our journey, or took the time to give feedback on what we found and our ideas for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the size of the report, a full copy of the report is available upon request. If you’d like to stay across any of the work coming out of the Service Innovation Lab, please join our &lt;a href=&quot;https://confirmsubscription.com/h/j/7AA94B673345A7D5&quot;&gt;mailing list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;White, V. &amp;amp; Jones, M (2017). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/assets/Uploads/SR372-Warm-dry-healthy2.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warm, dry, healthy? Insights from the 2015 House Condition Survey on insulation, ventilation, heating and mould in New Zealand houses (PDF 3.90MB)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. BRANZ Study Report SR372. Judgeford, New Zelaand: BRANZ Ltd. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>glen-thurston</name></author><category term="engagement" /><category term="collaboration" /><category term="renting a property" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rates Rebates (Te Whakamāmā i ngā Reiti)</title><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2018/11/30/Rates-Rebate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rates Rebates (Te Whakamāmā i ngā Reiti)" /><published>2018-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2018/11/30/Rates-Rebate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2018/11/30/Rates-Rebate/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR1.png&quot; alt=&quot;RR logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authored by:&lt;/strong&gt; Siobhan McCarthy and Glen Thurston&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;contents&quot;&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-The-Discovery&quot;&gt;The Discovery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-The-Alpha&quot;&gt;The Alpha&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Insights-Discovery-Alpha&quot;&gt;Insights from Discovery and Alpha&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Next-Steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Appendix1&quot;&gt;Appendix One - Service Blueprints&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Appendix2&quot;&gt;Appendix Two - Trend Analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Appendix3&quot;&gt;Appendix Three - Comparison between the web app &amp;amp; current paper application&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A collaborative initiative between Department of Internal Affairs and Local Authorities supported by the Service Innovation Lab&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Overview&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.govt.nz/browse/housing-and-property/getting-help-with-housing/getting-a-rates-rebate/#who-can-apply&quot;&gt;‘A Rates Rebates’&lt;/a&gt; is a subsidy (up to $630) for low-income homeowners on the cost of their residential rates. The subsidy is delivered by Local Councils and is administered by Central Government (specifically the Department of Internal Affairs - DIA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entitlement value is calculated by the cost of the rates, applicants income, and number of dependants. The maximum subsidy amount is reviewed yearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Service Innovation Working Group (SIWG) within the Digital Government Partnership supported by the GCDO, prioritised and approved an initiative to explore the design and delivery of a proactive service with the goal of being to create an automated service. Rates Rebates was identified as a service for this initiative based on research for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/lab-our-integrated-services-design-approach-and-summary/&quot;&gt;becoming a senior life event&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This collaborative initiative was between DIA as the lead agency (ie business owner) and Local Authorities (ie Councils) supported by the Service Innovation Lab (the Lab) in the delivery of the work through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ict.govt.nz/guidance-and-resources/accelerate/discovery/&quot;&gt;Discovery&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ict.govt.nz/guidance-and-resources/accelerate/alpha/&quot;&gt;Alpha&lt;/a&gt; phases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a phase of work called a ‘discovery’ the Rates Rebates service was mapped and reviewed, internal and external stakeholders were interviewed, and potential methods of service delivery were explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery revealed many opportunities at the system level to improve the experience for both the people applying for their entitlement and people delivering the service. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_viable_product&quot;&gt;A minimum viable product&lt;/a&gt; (MVP) was designed and developed between March—May 2018 and an online service for rebate applications was trialled in Tauranga from 21 May—30 September 2018 with Tauranga City Council. This phase of work was called an ‘alpha’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alpha was focused on testing system changes. Tauranga City Council, Auckland Council was involved with assisting with the design and test of the alpha and numerous councils have been watching progress closely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the discovery and the alpha identified that there is desirability to progress the alpha service to full production from both an applicant and local councils perspective and the Lab is currently supporting DIA to explore how to transition the alpha to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ict.govt.nz/guidance-and-resources/accelerate/beta/&quot;&gt;Beta&lt;/a&gt; (ie first live production).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report incompasses all the work the collaborative team (ie DIA, local authorities and the Lab) has been involved with to date with Rates Rebates. It contains background about the Rates Rebates scheme, insights found during both the discovery and alpha,  a description about the recent alpha work and the discovery that underpinned the work. Combined, this provides a complete picture of how we (ie the collaborative team) did the work, what we learned and our recommendations for making rates rebate an automated service that could could form part an integrated service for specific life events (eg Becoming a Senior, Needing Financial Assistance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Background&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-was-this-brought-to-the-service-innovation-lab&quot;&gt;Why was this brought to the Service Innovation Lab&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rates Rebates entitlement was identified as a proactive entitlement for the Service Innovation Lab to explore by the Service Innovation Working Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the large number of applicants who are Superannuitants, this is also a service that is considered to play a part in the “Becoming a Senior” life event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-has-been-involved&quot;&gt;Who has been involved?&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Involved&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discovery Phase&lt;/strong&gt;
Department of Internal Affairs, Tauranga City Council, Auckland Council, Wellington City Council, Ministry of Social Development, Inland Revenue, Assurity,  Service Innovation Lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alpha Phase&lt;/strong&gt;
Tauranga City Council, Department of Internal Affairs, Auckland Council, Service Innovation Lab,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-entitlement-in-numbers&quot;&gt;The entitlement in numbers&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2016/2017 rating year &lt;strong&gt;97,947&lt;/strong&gt; rebates were granted, of those &lt;strong&gt;80,486&lt;/strong&gt; were the full $610.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The maximum subsidy amount is reviewed yearly - for 2016/17 the maximum was $610. In 2017/18 the maximum is $620. In 2018/19 its $630.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trend shows the number of rebates granted each year going down. This is a well known trend and is mostly due to the income threshold not keeping in pace with the rise in superannuation payments year to year, leading to those on the couples super especially, gradually dropping out of eligibility. Other factors include housing affordability and lowering home ownership rates - &lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Appendix2&quot;&gt;Appendix Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; contains more information on this trend and causal factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is not enough data available at this time for us to know:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many apply and are rejected due to inconsistent implementation processes across council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many people are eligible across Aotearoa New Zealand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many know their eligibility or that the entitlement exists, and
How many choose to apply or not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Rating year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Maximum rebate&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Rebates granted&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Value (inc GST)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Average Rebate&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Full (maximum) rebates granted&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Average rebate granted &amp;lt; maximum&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2010-11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$570&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;112,181&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$59,131,590&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$527.11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91,941&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$332.27&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2011-12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$580&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;115,187&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$62,340,668&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$541.21&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;95,988&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$347.29&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2012-13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$590&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;111,021&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$60,231,307&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$542.52&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;90,857&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$328.59&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2013-14&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$595&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;106,416&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$58,086,259&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$545.84&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87,209&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$322.64&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2014-15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$605&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;104,410&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$58,092,996&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$556.39&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;86,047&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$328.63&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2015-16&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$610&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;102,208&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$57,102,376&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$558.69&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;83,737&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$326.07&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2016-17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$610&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;97,947&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$54,655,977&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$570.23&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80,486&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$318.40&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017-18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$620&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;97,609&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$55,496,610&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$568.56&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80,810&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$321.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rebate-amendment&quot;&gt;Rebate amendment&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Amendment&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2018 the Rates Rebate Amendment Act 2018 was passed that grants those who live in retirement villages eligibility to receive Rates Rebates, expanding the number of eligible by approximately 25,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data from last year suggests 36,618 people currently live in retirement villages, these are comprised of 28,168 units. Some of these units were already eligible to apply under the old legislation if they were rated separately and in the name of the resident. We don’t have numbers for this but it’s a minority of units, most units are newly covered by the recent legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High level estimate of units newly eligible to apply is around 25,000. The number actually eligible to receive a rebate will be much lower due to income levels and value of rates. For example, most couples aren’t eligible as the couples superannuation income, together with having relatively low rates precludes a lot of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-key-stakeholders&quot;&gt;Our key stakeholders&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Stakeholders&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ratepayers&lt;/strong&gt;
Those eligible for a rebate are people who own and live in their home with an income level below a formula determined by their rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local Government&lt;/strong&gt;
Application forms are accepted by Local Government, who do initial processing of the entitlement and apply it to applicants residential property rating accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Department of Internal Affairs (DIA)&lt;/strong&gt;
DIA administer the rebate, are responsible for the paper forms, which they deliver to councils, and are responsible for the payments of rebates to be made to local councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pain-points-for-applicants-and-system&quot;&gt;Pain points for applicants and system&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Painpoints&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the discovery and the alpha phases we explored all aspects of the rates rebate experience from the perspectives of the users or applicants who apply for their entitlement and the people who are involved in the system of facilitating, checking and approving the applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;applicants&quot;&gt;Applicants&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The complexity of application&lt;/strong&gt; creates a poor customer experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of awareness of rebate entitlement&lt;/strong&gt; for potential applicants and in social security support systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citizen time&lt;/strong&gt;
The current system is estimated to cost $1m in citizen time alone&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Issues affecting mobility and access&lt;/strong&gt;
Due to many applicants being over 65 and/or with disabilities, the impact of the requirement of Statutory Declaration in front of a witness impacts accessibility for the core customer group.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;system&quot;&gt;System&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The process is very &lt;strong&gt;manual&lt;/strong&gt; and involves &lt;strong&gt;costly double handling&lt;/strong&gt;. Applicants must fill in the same information and apply every year even when their information does not change.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preventable &lt;strong&gt;cost of implementation to councils&lt;/strong&gt; and wait times for payments back to councils from DIA&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prescriptive legislation&lt;/strong&gt; preventing an end-to-end digital experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-discovery&quot;&gt;The discovery&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-The-Discovery&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In​ ​September​ 2017 ​the ​team​ ​kicked​ ​off​ ​a​ ​three-week​ ​discovery​ ​sprint,​ ​exploring​ ​how​ ​subsidies​ ​are provided​ ​to​ ​New​ ​Zealanders​ ​and​ ​what​ ​ ​that​ ​could look​ ​like​ ​in​ ​the​ ​future,​ ​with​ ​a​ ​focus​ ​on​ ​Rates Rebates.​ ​Rates​ ​Rebates​ ​are​ ​an​ ​entitlement​ ​that​ ​has​ ​been​ ​identified​ ​as​ ​a​ ​key​ ​pain​ ​point​ ​for​ ​applicants (low-income​ ​property​ ​owners​ ​for​ ​primary​ ​residences),​ ​as​ ​well​ ​as​ ​for​ ​Local​ ​and​ ​Central​ ​Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery sprint included service designers, user researchers and subject matter experts from the Department of Internal Affairs (the Service Innovation team as well as the Rates Rebates team), Auckland Council, Tauranga Council, Wellington Council, the Ministry for Social Development and the Inland Revenue Department with support from Assurity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;week-one---kick-off&quot;&gt;Week One - Kick off&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;focus-points&quot;&gt;Focus points&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team identified the following focus points for the three week sprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand​ ​and​ ​Complement​&lt;/strong&gt; - Previous Rates Rebates insights focused on the process from an applicant perspective, our team will collect and analyse insight from multiple perspectives including Central and Local Government agencies. We are also looking for additional applicant types that have not been spoken to before and understand the size and demographics of the eligibility groups.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local​ ​and​ ​Global​ ​Picture&lt;/strong&gt;​ - We are exploring the local and global community and identifying similar concepts, prototypes and entitlement models that we can factor into our concept development.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data​ ​Path​&lt;/strong&gt; - Exploring the data path of the process, data ownership, authority and declaration and what this could mean for implementation of any automated concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thinking​ ​Big/Parallel​ ​Value​&lt;/strong&gt; - How could this be applied across all of government services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;week-two---customer-research-and-journey-mapping&quot;&gt;Week Two - Customer research and journey mapping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;service-blueprint&quot;&gt;Service blueprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Service Map The Rates Rebates Process touches many agencies. We mapped the journey to see touch points for rebates customers, front stage (agency work visible to the rebate customer), and backstage (agency work not visible to the rebate customer). It showed a very complex picture with a lot of pain across users, Councils and Central government agencies. Considering this entitlement is a maximum of $610 per year, it requires a lot of cost and time from all participants in the process to administer.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Service Blueprint&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To view the journey in more detail, please use this link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/drawings/d/1G3cs66o7u-xwJWr2FT46cd5UivJ-HojpcS3I-Q5bSOY/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;https://docs.google.com/drawings/d/1G3cs66o7u-xwJWr2FT46cd5UivJ-HojpcS3I-Q5bSOY/edit?usp=sharing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;personas&quot;&gt;Personas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We created the following personas based on the customer groups identified to compliment the personas made in the previous discovery work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;working-mother&quot;&gt;Working mother&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hannah lives in Southland, looking after her three kids and doing some freelance work in her spare time. She is very capable, but going into town can be a bother – she borrows a car from her neighbour and it’s not always available. Because she lives rurally, she likes to do more things online. She’s short on time and money is always tight. She has found out about the Rates Rebates and wants to get it – but she’s also short on time and not sure if the bother is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Working Mother&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;superannuant&quot;&gt;Superannuant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jennifer is a retiree living in a block of flats in Wellington city. She doesn’t drive anymore, but manages to get around fine on public transport. She thinks of herself as pretty independent, but sometimes she needs to help with her finances and paperwork – she’s not as good at reading the fine print anymore. She uses an iPad to look at FaceBook and the news – but doesn’t do much else online and doesn’t like the idea of her personal details being somewhere out there. She’s a repeat applicant for the Rates Rebates, and considers it a nice bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Superannuant&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;supported-living-dependant&quot;&gt;Supported Living dependant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George lives in a suburb in Tauranga. He suffers from a physical disability, and depends heavily on his support person for any physical activity. Money is tight and he budgets carefully – allocating all of the money that comes in. When there is a delay, it’s a real issue. He has lots of interaction with government to claim various benefits and he is comfortable with doing things online - but he doesn’t have his own computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Supported Living Dependant&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;week-3---concept-development-and-testing&quot;&gt;Week 3 - Concept development and testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tested 3 concepts, hypothetical ways the process of rebates might work, based on data sharing between agencies, to help make the process easier and efficient. We tested the concepts with those we interviewed to find out their thoughts and opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spoke to 17 ratepayers that covered different demographics to map their experience and pain points. A large portion of them were women and retired, building on previous research from Internal Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Assisted automation opt-in&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;option-1---assisted-automation-opt-in&quot;&gt;Option 1 - Assisted automation opt-in&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were varied reactions to this option. Some said they saw issues with it being online, mentioning they know a lot of people in their circles who get rebates and do not have computers or feel comfortable using them. Others liked this but often said they preferred option 3 after they had seen all options. Some suggested that they liked the idea of the service being provided by phone, and suggested that there may be a way for them to make a verbal declaration in place of Statutory Declaration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Automatically apply rebate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;option-2---automatically-apply-rebate&quot;&gt;Option 2 - Automatically apply rebate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This option was usually popular, until option 3 was shown and then they decided that this was something they did not actually want. As they were unsure what this would mean if the information was wrong or felt uncomfortable for the govt to be talking about them and deciding things without their knowledge. Many felt that this option was a bit “big brother.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auto populate data&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;option-3---auto-populate-data&quot;&gt;Option 3 - Auto populate data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Option 3 was the most popular. People were usually most comfortable with this option as they felt that it still let them be in control, but also made the complex process less work for them. Some felt uncomfortable about their data being shared without their permission and knowledge, and didn’t like the idea of the government ‘talking about me’ as they did not trust the government completely. Many users had the attitude of ‘they already do this/know this information anyway’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-alpha&quot;&gt;The Alpha&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-The-Alpha&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-future-of-the-rates-rebates-service&quot;&gt;The Future of the Rates Rebates Service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/labplus-rates-rebates-discovery-report/&quot;&gt;Discovery phase&lt;/a&gt; there were a number of opportunities identified for service improvement. We also identified barriers from the prescriptive legislation, an Act written in 1973, that impacts what is possible for digital service delivery in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the three concepts tested, based on data sharing between agencies to help make the process easier and efficient, option 3 (auto-populate data) was the most popular. People were most comfortable with this option as they felt that it still let them have control, while also making the complex process less work. There are some issues with the legislation around the witnessing of forms, this could prove to be a barrier to this option being easily implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking these findings we were able to set a goal of what would be possible to achieve for a minimum viable product (MVP), that would support a better Rates Rebates service to be brought into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/standards-and-guidance/strategy-and-planning/digital-lifecycle/&quot;&gt;Alpha stage&lt;/a&gt; of testing. This Alpha service has been designed to make it easier for people to identify their eligibility and then apply for the rebate with less effort and stress. It was also designed to simplify service delivery for the council from the current very manual and paper heavy process to a simple, faster and digital service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Discovery, the collaborative team tested concepts with ratepayers showing different levels of proactive delivery. The majority of those we spoke to preferred the concept that had some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/lab-potential-future-states-for-government-service-delivery/&quot;&gt;proactive delivery&lt;/a&gt;, but had a process of consenting, to ensure that they retained control of the situation, rather than having the rebate automatically applied. This was an important factor in an MVP design, moving into the Alpha stage, for Rates Rebates. As it doesn’t assume a fully proactive delivery in order to meet user expectations of maintaining control throughout the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We knew that we wanted to improve the service for people, and some constraints from the Rates Rebate Act meant we weren’t able to completely flip the process on its head. The Rates Rebate Act requires the applicant to submit a form, which is then signed and witnessed by an authorised person, usually a service centre staff member at the council when an application is submitted, similar to a statutory declaration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this knowledge, and knowledge of digital best practice, we were able to set our goals for an MVP.  We assembled a team of subject matter experts from the initial discovery team, and brought on developers to help make this digital service a reality. This includes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aucklandcouncil.govt.nz/Pages/default.aspx&quot;&gt;Auckland Council&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tauranga.govt.nz/&quot;&gt;Tauranga City Council&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dia.govt.nz/&quot;&gt;Department of Internal Affairs&lt;/a&gt;, supported by the Service Innovation Lab team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;criteria-for-alpha-to-test---our-scope&quot;&gt;Criteria for alpha to test - our scope&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Councils clearly articulated the need to address the signature/witness legislative barrier to enable a fully digital streamlined service and this has been addressed by DIA Legal advice. Through discussion, the Council then outlined the following specific areas where the proposed Alpha could create immediate value which would be used as success criteria for Alpha and beyond:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An &lt;strong&gt;increase in uptake&lt;/strong&gt; of the rebate and &lt;strong&gt;decreased time, effort and stress&lt;/strong&gt; for users that use Alpha.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;proportional drop in the refused applications&lt;/strong&gt;, and we can measure web analytics of how many users roughly started the process and how many applications were completed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If Alpha involves only digital forms, then there would be a &lt;strong&gt;decrease in time and cost of processing payment from DIA&lt;/strong&gt;, however, if the Alpha involves both paper and digital, this success criteria is not relevant to Alpha.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving to a digital signature of a digital form, even if done in person, should dramatically &lt;strong&gt;reduce the resources and courier costs&lt;/strong&gt; in administering this rebate for Councils, and should reduce effort for DIA.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Through user research we will test current state against Alpha and should see an &lt;strong&gt;improved satisfaction level&lt;/strong&gt; from ratepayers who use the services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding the collection of email address within the service would &lt;strong&gt;improve the ability to digitally deliver&lt;/strong&gt; other services for Council.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;additional-success-criteria-after-alpha-would-require-integration-with-tauranga-city-council-systems-once-alpha-proves-successful&quot;&gt;Additional success criteria after Alpha (would require integration with Tauranga City Council systems once Alpha proves successful)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To reduce the manual processes for helpdesk filling in and doing data entry of the application forms should &lt;strong&gt;improve the speed of delivery at help desk&lt;/strong&gt;, creating a small improvement both in the users experience and in help desk productivity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By simplifying and digitising the process, we hope to see an &lt;strong&gt;improvement in the turnaround time of batches sent to DIA and faster payments made to Council&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-desirable-components-for-project-to-investigate&quot;&gt;Other desirable components for project to investigate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage &lt;strong&gt;consistency of messaging&lt;/strong&gt; across councils and agencies for Rates Rebates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Help &lt;strong&gt;address user perceptions&lt;/strong&gt;, that ‘the entitlement is being made purposely hard to prevent people getting it’, by &lt;strong&gt;making it easier to find, assess and apply for&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-research---diving-deeper&quot;&gt;Further research - diving deeper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We dived even deeper into understanding the service delivery and what is possible. By examining legislation, technology systems used to run the current service, and modes of delivery we created detailed service blueprints of the current and future states, testing them against each other and our goals for the service improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We looked into how data was being submitted by ratepayers in their paper applications, and what forms this data took when digitised, transported, and processed. We looked over the form and worked on how the language could be improved for plain English, and how form fields could be made easier to complete. For example, when asking an applicant’s income, we could provide an option to press a button to state that they are receiving NZ Superannuation, rather than asking them what dollar amount that is, as we already know the figure limits for superannuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Appendix1&quot;&gt;Appendix One&lt;/a&gt; contains service blueprints that describe how the current service works, the alpha used in the Tauranga pilot and a potential future state of a fully automated proactive service future state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-the-alpha-works---user-interface-design&quot;&gt;How the alpha works - user interface design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;making-it-easy&quot;&gt;Making it easy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR9.png&quot; width=&quot;425px&quot; alt=&quot;ipad device running the rates rebate application&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make it easy we built a web application (web app) for the ratepayer applicants to use as the basis of the alpha. Applicants can learn if they were eligible for a Rates Rebate in the current year by entering their address. We created a widget where the applicant only types their address, which is auto-completed for them, and their Rates appear - it uses publicly available data which we obtained in collaboration with the Tauranga City Council. Once the applicant enters their income and number of dependants, they get an indication of their Rates Rebate. If they provide accurate information, they will get an accurate calculation - it’s all in one place,  the user interface design guides people through the process giving them the information needed to help them make a decision whether its worthwhile for them to apply or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the applicant calculated they are eligible and chooses to apply, they are then presented with more information to ensure they understand the definitions of income and dependants. We were able to eliminate the need for paper in this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once an application is submitted online, the applicant then must visit the Tauranga City Council service centre, where they then make their statutory declaration on a touchscreen iPad using a stylus. The signature is saved and can be sent digitally to DIA. We could not avoid asking the applicant to travel to a city council service centre, because the legislation requires a witnessed declaration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web application frontend was built in ReactJS, with a jsonapi.org server created with JSONAPI Suite on Ruby on Rails. Signatures were captured using “signature_pad” npm module. The web app was built in five weeks. All components used were open source, and available on github.com for other agencies to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eligibility-calculator&quot;&gt;Eligibility calculator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research told us people applying for the rates rebate often don’t know how much they earn. As many are on Superannuation or Work and Income benefits we can ask if they’re on one of these income sources, as the amounts are known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also found that there was some embarrassment about income and about asking for any form of help which was a barrier to applying, so we designed an anonymous calculation step at the beginning of the service so people don’t have to go through a full application before they find out if they are eligible for anything (which is the current process). We found users that had gone through days of effort to apply, only to discover they were entitled to 30 cents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR10.png&quot; alt=&quot;User journey for pilot digital application&quot; /&gt;
(Above: an example of the user journey when using the pilot digital application)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;user-interfaceuser-experience-development&quot;&gt;User Interface/User Experience development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The user interface, online eligibility calculator and web app went through testing with citizens, Tauranga City Council Service and Support Centre staff, as well as with DIA Rates Rebates staff throughout development. Testing with prototypes built in Atomic, a web based mockup tool, meant that we were able to make changes on the fly while testing and getting feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To read more on this prototyping and see some of the work in progress prototypes go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/labplus-rates-rebates-prototyping/&quot;&gt;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/labplus-rates-rebates-prototyping/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feedback on the prototypes was very positive. There were many iterations of language style used and testing helped us find language that we felt was appropriate, and read as the plainest English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feedback-from-digital-pilot-users-in-tauranga&quot;&gt;Feedback from digital pilot users in Tauranga&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I didn’t know government things could be like this”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;- User testing&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m partially blind, so if things are on a computer I can zoom in and read them”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;- First applicant on Tauranga pilot&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“That was easy, wasn’t it!”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;- Pilot applicant&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I would do it online next time”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;- Pilot applicant&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“That was easier than I thought!”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;- Pilot applicant &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;opportunities-for-digitising-the-application&quot;&gt;Opportunities for digitising the application&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By making the application digital we were able to show where improvements could be made to the system and processes of the service. There are opportunities for integration with Rating Information Databases from local councils, local council information management systems, as well as central government systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other benefits of a digital service are that changes to the entitlement can be implemented in a shorter period of time, such as the income threshold and maximum entitlement, which are reviewed every year and often changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investing in a creating a digital application channel and changing legislation to remove the need for a statutory declaration would mean a lower cost of implementation to citizens, councils, and central government (ie DIA, IRD and MSD) due to reduced processing times and cost of printing and moving paper forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application process was entirely digital&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and removed the need for paper, as well as considerably reducing the time for customers and processing time for Councils. The estimated time for an applicant to complete the paper form is 25 minutes, with the digital application taking roughly 4 minutes&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Councils also found this reduced time of processing, as they could copy and paste applicant information into their systems instead of typing out by hand, as well as time saved from applications being unable to be submitted with gaps or incomplete sections in the digital form, which is common for paper forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Appendix3&quot;&gt;Appendix 3&lt;/a&gt; shows a physical comparison of the web app vs the current paper application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;insights-from-discovery-and-alpha-&quot;&gt;Insights from discovery and alpha &lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Insights-Discovery-Alpha&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;applicants-insights&quot;&gt;Applicants insights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;customer-segmentation&quot;&gt;Customer segmentation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of current applicants are retired, around 80% of applicants receive New Zealand Superannuation. There is a misconception that Rates Rebates require you to be on NZ Superannuation to be eligible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supported Living payment recipients and solo parents are another significant demographic of applicants, although more research is needed to confirm demographics due to the lack of information collected on applicants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lack-of-awareness&quot;&gt;Lack of awareness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that there are many ratepayers who are eligible but do not know about the entitlement. Council rebates and contact centre staff are worried that &lt;strong&gt;there are a lot of people out there that need a rebate, but do not know about it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research showed that many people &lt;strong&gt;find out about the entitlement via word of mouth&lt;/strong&gt;. – almost by accident, rather than from direct messaging from Local or Central Government.
Examples from our research include one ratepayer who had experienced a change in their financial situation after being diagnosed with a serious illness, who was informed about the entitlement from a friend who had learnt about Rates Rebates from the doctor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When rates are not paid, this is a &lt;strong&gt;trigger for the Council to proactively reach out&lt;/strong&gt; to applicants about applying for a rebate. This can often be the way a ratepayer finds out that Rates Rebates exist and that they are entitled to one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;complexity&quot;&gt;Complexity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customers do not find completing the application easy or enjoyable. Collating their information and obtaining evidence from other agencies have been identified as a pain point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was often said that &lt;strong&gt;you have to know the system to get the entitlement&lt;/strong&gt;, and the application is quite difficult and complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments from citizens interviewed include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Doesn’t the government know all this stuff about me anyway?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If this is what I have to do to get some money do I really want to do it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People won’t take the money if the value of the trade is too low” [e.g. time, giving up their personal information]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;accessibility&quot;&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both council staff and ratepayers commented that at peak application time, the service centres become very busy with rebate applicants and described scenes where the lines were long, with many in the lines being elderly and council staff bringing out chairs for those who struggle to stand for too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some said it &lt;strong&gt;“feels like a hospital waiting room”&lt;/strong&gt; and others worry about how they will complete their Rates Rebates applications when they are older and less able-bodied and/or able-minded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;requirement and logistics of needing to have the application witnessed&lt;/strong&gt; is a big pain point - especially for those with low mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a user perception that there needs to be options for service delivery other than Digital - &lt;strong&gt;“What if they don’t have a computer?”&lt;/strong&gt;
Applicants asked: &lt;strong&gt;“Why can’t you just do it over the phone?”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cultural-expectations&quot;&gt;Cultural expectations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common perception from successful applicants was that &lt;strong&gt;there are a lot of people worse off than them&lt;/strong&gt; who are more deserving to get a rebate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some applicants expressed that rebates made them &lt;strong&gt;feel as if they begging for money&lt;/strong&gt; now that their main source of income was NZ Superannuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quotes from applicants interviewed include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If I’m entitled to something just give it to me”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It felt like a cross-examination”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It feels like airing your underwear”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since becoming a Superannuitant “I am a second class citizen”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s embarrassing having to ask [for a rebate] but you are entitled”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;trust-in-digital-and-government&quot;&gt;Trust in digital and government&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single poor experience with computers or automated systems can colour how much trust a customer has around automation. Many ratepayers we interviewed mentioned either themselves or someone they know who’d had a bad experience such as either being scammed or having had a poor customer experience with a company with an online component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customers often find &lt;strong&gt;correspondence from government threatening&lt;/strong&gt; when it’s addressed to them as an individual.  This can lead to communications about entitlements either being missed or misunderstood, as citizens feel that they will not be contacted by the government unless there is a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;system-and-process-insights&quot;&gt;System and process insights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;inefficient-process&quot;&gt;Inefficient process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process is very manual and involves &lt;strong&gt;costly double handling&lt;/strong&gt;. Applicants must fill in the same information and apply every year even when their information does not change. Applicants often submit incomplete and incorrect forms which compounds problems further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ratepayers find the application confusing&lt;/strong&gt;, leading to forms often completed wrongly , or required fields left blank. If this happens, the applicant must be contacted and then the application re-submitted, &lt;strong&gt;delaying when the rebate can be granted&lt;/strong&gt; which is often at a time when it’s needed most. This results in more double handling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cost-to-council&quot;&gt;Cost to council&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Councils can be left waiting for DIA payments to come through after they have discounted customers rates. Many councils are also unhappy with the cost of implementing the facilitating and checking of an entitlement application which cost them staff that could be better used in more high value contacts with their ratepayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;peak-times-are-hard-to-staff-and-manage&quot;&gt;Peak times are hard to staff and manage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of applications come at the start of the rating year in August. Due to the number of applications, compared to other months of the year, councils often hire temporary staff for a number of months to help process rebate forms, and DIA have similar issues related to staffing  (ie staff are moved from other areas to help out) during this busy period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;service-centre-support-and-success-of-applications&quot;&gt;Service centre support and success of applications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Council representatives are an important part of the process&lt;/strong&gt; and are seen as visible evidence that something is being done to progress their application. For some customers, Council representatives make it worry free and take the stress out of it. Councils often receive thank you cards and calls from customers who have gotten a rebate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The council representatives &lt;strong&gt;knowledge and willingness to help&lt;/strong&gt; make the difference to the experience and success of applications. If there wasn’t this level of assistance, then it is less likely to be a positive experience. But this great customer experience comes at a cost for work that is considered low value compared to more complex ratepayer queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Wouldn’t it be great to not need a 50 page handbook” Council staff on understanding Rates Rebate Act (1973) and DIA rules&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;inconsistent-messaging-from-councils&quot;&gt;Inconsistent messaging from councils&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;inconsistencies across councils on implementation&lt;/strong&gt;, e.g. when applicants are asked to provide proof, and what information that they give to customers. We mapped information provided on council websites about Rates Rebates and found a large variation in amount and types of information to inform ratepayers about rebates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;prescriptive-legislation&quot;&gt;Prescriptive legislation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legislation is very prescriptive, making it impossible to create an end-to-end digital service. This is impacting the customer experience. The requirement for a statutory declaration has been identified as a key issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Next-Steps&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the discovery and the alpha identified that there is desirability to progress the alpha service to full production from both an applicant and local councils perspective and the Lab is currently supporting DIA to explore how to transition the alpha to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ict.govt.nz/guidance-and-resources/accelerate/beta/&quot;&gt;Beta&lt;/a&gt;.  A beta is developing a service to meet demands of a live environment, including understanding how to build and scale the service while continuously meeting user needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transition work involves understanding the viability of the service from a business owner perspective (ie development, implementation and ongoing costs) and the feasibility from a technology perspective of implementing the alpha into production. The goal being to identify a range of options that could be applied to deliver a production version of the service for DIA leadership consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next steps will consist of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a workshop to explore the collective goals we have for the service and initial options that could be explored in more detail post workshop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Detailed exploration of the initial options and identification of other if appropriate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recommendation and decision by DIA to stop or commit to a roadmap for delivery that could include engaging with more Councils, more user testing and research, more development or full development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DIA as custodian of the Rates Rebates will ultimately make a decision based on the work done and their own priorities on whether or not to continue the development to full production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Zealand Society of Local Government Managers (SOLGM) has made a submission for the Local Government Regulatory Systems Amendment Bill, to better support online applications for rates rebate by removing the requirement for an officer of the council (or anyone) to witness the statutory declaration. This would make the implementation of a truly online application process possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alpha identified in practice how the statutory declaration is out of step with digital service delivery. This issue is being referred to the required Policy teams to investigate if statutory declarations could be replaced for other services as well as the Rates Rebates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommendations-if-approved-to-production&quot;&gt;Recommendations if approved to production&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the alpha is developed further to production we recommend exploring these areas for service improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Work with Inland Revenue and Ministry of Social Development to allow for &lt;strong&gt;consented income testing&lt;/strong&gt; to make it easier for applicants to prove their income.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Work with other agencies such as Ministry of Social Development to &lt;strong&gt;integrate the rates rebate application into applications for other services&lt;/strong&gt;, such as applying for Jobseekers, Supported Living, NZ Superannuation etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consistent messaging across agencies&lt;/strong&gt; - After discovering the inconsistent messages about rebates across councils and agencies, there is potential for work to improve consistency across councils on messaging regarding Rates Rebates. We mapped the information across councils with large variations found:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1uHktpWj03FKFX0F0Hn7GK9pg1sMxBKaaPfjA8Gd_ra8/edit#gid=0&quot;&gt;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1uHktpWj03FKFX0F0Hn7GK9pg1sMxBKaaPfjA8Gd_ra8/edit#gid=0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential for greater link with Superannuation&lt;/strong&gt; - A large portion of rebate receivers are retired and on superannuation. There is potential to use this as a vehicle to help either gain awareness of the entitlement and/or to use this to make application easier. Many councils do not verify income if the applicant is on super, as many on super do not know their gross income and are on the same amount.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage more user groups&lt;/strong&gt; - On testing, we suggest more engagement with a range of user groups who require additional relationship building then the short time that the sprint process allowed. It would also benefit system improvement to invest in understanding cultural attitudes around receiving money/help to improve uptake of the entitlement. This came up in research as an issue, but due to limited timeframes and scope was not able to be investigated deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Translation to other languages&lt;/strong&gt; - Councils identified that they had applicants who had low levels of fluency in English and found applying difficult. It was common for the council teams to find a workmate who spoke the language deal with these applications, and also for these staff to move on leaving the teams unable to deal with applicants with low English. Having a digital application would allow for pages to translated and easily switched to languages such as Samoan, Hindi and Mandarin.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix-one---service-blueprints&quot;&gt;Appendix One - Service Blueprints&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Appendix1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DIA Rates rebates completed forms processing: Current state&lt;/strong&gt;
This blueprint helped us to see where manual handling was in place once forms were sent to DIA, and where opportunities for cost/time saving through digitisation could be found.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR11.png&quot; alt=&quot;Current state&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rates rebates Alpha Blueprint&lt;/strong&gt;
This blueprint shows how the Rates Rebates pilot in Tauranga service structured, and helps show what needed to be built and what existing systems could be used without changes required.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR12.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alpha blueprint&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Future State Blueprint&lt;/strong&gt;
This blueprint shows a potential future where information sharing between agencies is used to provide proactive delivery of the rebates entitlement.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR13.png&quot; alt=&quot;Future state blueprint&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix-two---trends-analysis&quot;&gt;Appendix Two - Trends analysis&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Appendix2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following charts describe the number of claims made for the last three years and the timings of when the applications are made to the Councils. The majority of applications are made in August each year and to mitigate the high workload on existing council staff, temporary staff are brought in to help process these. DIA audit these applications and their busy time falls between Aug and Oct when they verify the claims.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR14.png&quot; alt=&quot;Volume by claimed, refused, cancelled per year&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasons why claims are refused and cancelled include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The applicant earned more income than&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The application was incorrectly completed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The applicant didn’t live at the location advised&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The applicant had an undeclared partner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is anecdotal evidence from this study most are due to misunderstandings of the form and the application process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR15.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tauranga Ciy Council Applications processed per month &amp;amp; year&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dropping number of rebates claimed each year&lt;/strong&gt;
The number of Rates Rebates claimed each year has been dropping. This is a well known trend and is mostly due to the income threshold not keeping in pace with the rise in superannuation payments year to year, leading to those on the couples super especially, gradually dropping out of eligibility. There are some other factors that are potentially affecting this, including rates of homeownership and other factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Home Ownership rates lowest in 66 years&lt;/strong&gt;
  In 2017 homeownership rates in New Zealand were at the lowest they had been for 66 years at 63.2 percent of people today live in a home they owned, the lowest rate of ownership since the 1951 Census with rates recorded at 61.2 percent&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Awareness of Rates Rebates&lt;/strong&gt;
  There is anecdotal evidence that suggests that awareness of the entitlement is low. Due to current measurement practices we don’t know how many people are eligible and what are the reasons that they don’t apply (eg they choose not to, the application process is seen as complicated and confusing). The later point is consistent problem with most government services or any services for that matter - why does someone not use your service? To answer this question for Rates Rebates would require data analysis and user research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost of housing increasing&lt;/strong&gt;
  Stats NZ data shows an upwards trend in the cost of housing since 2007. There has been an 8.0 percent increase in the weekly cost of housing from 2014/2014 to 2015/2016. Stats NZ say that this increase was mostly due to households spending more on mortgage payments (up 12.8 percent) and property rates (up 9.6 percent). In comparison, renting costs over the same period increased by 1.8 percent&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR16.png&quot; alt=&quot;Housing costs as a percentage of total household income&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR17.png&quot; alt=&quot;Average weekly household expenditure&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Zealand’s access to the internet&lt;/strong&gt;
  Internet NZ reports that approximately connection&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This has an impact on people’s ability to find out about their entitlements with most service providers moving to digital channels. It also put more emphasis on designing for mobile as this will be the preferred channel that people will access internet in the future. Continuing development of the rates rebate alpha will need to keep in mind both of these points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix-three---comparison-between-the-web-app-and-current-paper-application&quot;&gt;Appendix Three - Comparison between the web app and current paper application&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Appendix3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a physical comparison of the web app vs the current paper application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-length-of-the-web-app-process&quot;&gt;The length of the web app process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR18.png&quot; alt=&quot;The length of the web app process&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-current-4-page-paper-form&quot;&gt;The current 4 page paper form&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR19.png&quot; alt=&quot;Page 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR20.png&quot; alt=&quot;Page 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR21.png&quot; alt=&quot;Page 3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Rates-Rebates/RR22.png&quot; alt=&quot;Page 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The maximum subsidy amount is reviewed yearly - for 2016/17 the maximum was $610. In 2017/18 the maximum is $620. In 2018/19 its $630. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Based on Treasury CBAx Cost Benefit Analysis calculator &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There was still a need for the applicant to come into the Council office to sign and get their application witnessed however this was also done digitally - no paper needed. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This does not take into account the time and effort to go into the Council office and sign the digitally Understanding how long that this could take depends on each applicant’s circumstances. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Home ownership rates lowest in 66 years according to Statistics NZ - New Zealand Herald &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nzherald.co.nz/business/news/article.cfm?c_id=3&amp;amp;objectid=11779664&quot;&gt;https://www.nzherald.co.nz/business/news/article.cfm?c_id=3&amp;amp;objectid=11779664&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Household expenditure statistics: Year ended June 2016 – corrected, Stats NZ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stats.govt.nz/information-releases/household-expenditure-statistics-year-ended-june-2016&quot;&gt;https://www.stats.govt.nz/information-releases/household-expenditure-statistics-year-ended-june-2016&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;State of the Internet 2017 Report- Internet NZ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>glen-thurston</name></author><category term="rates rebate" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the Notice of Sale Process</title><link href="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2018/10/12/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-process/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the Notice of Sale Process" /><published>2018-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2018/10/12/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-process</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://serviceinnovationlab.github.io//2018/10/12/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-process/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authored by:&lt;/strong&gt; Glen Thurston and Nadia Webster&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;contents&quot;&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-InSummary&quot;&gt;In summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-WhatIsNoticeOfSale&quot;&gt;What is the notice of sale and why is it important?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-PossibleSolution&quot;&gt;Possible solution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-NextSteps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exploring-the-notice-of-sale-process&quot;&gt;Exploring the Notice of Sale process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exploring opportunities to improve the notice of sale process as part of the life event of ‘selling and buying a property’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A collaboration between:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The All of Government Service Innovation Lab&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Auckland Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Land Information New Zealand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tauranga City Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wellington City Council&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whangarei District Council&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-summary&quot;&gt;In summary&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-InSummary&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2018, a collaboration led by the all of government Service Innovation Lab with Auckland Council, Land Information New Zealand (Valuer General), Tauranga City Council, Wellington City Council and Whangarei District Council explored the Notice of Sale (the notice) process as part of the ‘selling and buying a property’ life event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This group believe that there are a range of possible solutions to improve the notice; for the benefit of people selling and buying property, their agents (ie real estate agent, solicitors, conveyancers), Councils and government agencies teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During August, the group explored:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The role of the notice and its importance,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goals for the future of the notice,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pain points and experiences that people and organisations involved with the notice are having,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Potential opportunities/solutions for improving the process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work was completed in three parts, a current state review with the Wellington based group members, a design intensive in Auckland (13-16 August) followed by the write up of the findings of both the review and the design intensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this work was to help the group of interested parties identify a path forward to improve the notice process. It helps scope up future design work that would be needed to explore the opportunities in more depth to ascertain their desirability from a user perspective, viability from a business sustainability perspective and feasibility from a technical perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design intensive identified the following next steps that are needed to continue this work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The need for a sponsor(s) to help drive continuing this work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Lab could lead a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/standards-and-guidance/strategy-and-planning/digital-lifecycle/discovery/&quot;&gt;discovery&lt;/a&gt; with the support of this group to investigate the preferred data based possible solution in more detail to test its viability, feasibility and desirability.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Councils collectively or individually could investigate the other two solutions identified; in the intensive; Improve communication between Councils and Solicitors and data validation flags to help select the correct process to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-notice-of-sale-and-why-is-it-important&quot;&gt;What is the notice of sale and why is it important?&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-WhatIsNoticeOfSale&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Notice of Sale (the notice) acts a conduit of sales and/or property owner information in the property transfer process and its a legal requirement that it must be supplied to a Local Authority&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (ie Councils) as part of the Local Government (Rating) Act 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a Council the notice is typically the first contact they have about the transfer and importantly the new owner of the property. This allows them to update the rating information to send out the rates notice to them. The notice includes valuable sale information where a sale is involved (eg tells them how much the property sold) for which is important for the valuation purposes as it helps give an indication on the valuations for an area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rates and valuations are linked together and the notice is one of the key inputs into this process. The notice gives more information and data about the property that helps to give a better indication of valuation and therefore the rates to charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-rating-and-valuation-process&quot;&gt;The rating and valuation process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Valuation cycle &amp;amp; Local Authority actions feeds into the Setting and billing of rates, then to Property Owner&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Flow chart showing that Valuation cycle &amp;amp; Local Authority actions feeds into the Setting and billing of rates, then to Property Owner.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the rating process the notice also acts another way to provide information that the property title has changed too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-notice-of-sale-and-its-relation-to-rating-and-valuation&quot;&gt;The notice of sale and its relation to rating and valuation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(also see &lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Appendix1&quot;&gt;Appendix 1&lt;/a&gt; for the key concepts required under legislation and what triggers a change of ownership, and see &lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Appendix2&quot;&gt;Appendix 2 Data Map&lt;/a&gt; for what data is collected at each step in the process)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Notice of Sale decision tree&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Notice of Sale decision tree. &lt;strong&gt;Path 1&lt;/strong&gt; - Notice of change of ratepayer and/or their contact details of whole or part of the rating unit; Council finance team accountable fo calculation of rates. This is Audited by DIA; Council valuation team accountable for valuation data being correct. This is audited by LINZ valuer general. They determine structure of data extracts for comparable analysis. &lt;strong&gt;Path 2&lt;/strong&gt; - Notice of change of title (i.e. creation of a new title and cancellation of existing title); Register of Titles; Valuation Service Providers (VSP). They are accountable for the calculation of valuations. Councils are also required to provde the correct data/information to contirbute to the calculation.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notice must contain these points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The full name and address of the purchaser or transferee; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the case of a sale, the sale price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has to be supplied to the Council within one month after the sale or transfer of a rating unit by the person selling it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key legislative references are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.legislation.govt.nz/act/public/2002/0006/latest/DLM132269.html?search=ts_act%40bill%40regulation%40deemedreg_Local+Government+(Ratings)+Act+2002_resel_25_a&amp;amp;p=1&quot;&gt;Sections 31 - 33 and 36 of the Local Government (Ratings) Act 2002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.legislation.govt.nz/act/public/1998/0069/latest/DLM427713.html?search=ts_act%40bill%40regulation%40deemedreg_Rating+Valuation+Act+1998_resel_25_a&amp;amp;p=1&quot;&gt;Section 52 of the Rating Valuation Act 1998&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no prescribed form for the notice or methods to transmit the information to Councils. The notices vary depending on the other information requirements that Councils request or what solicitors typically want to send to support the sale. The QV sales direct online form was originally built around what is mandatory but has been amended over time based on solicitor and council requirements; most notably contact details for new owner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also no definition for the term ‘property’ as it’s not a clear concept. From a rating perspective at Councils it’s the &lt;em&gt;title and rating unit&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;statistics&quot;&gt;Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the LINZ Rating Valuation Data set, the following table describes the number of sales between 2014 to 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;number-of-sales-2014-2017&quot;&gt;Number of Sales 2014-2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table showing the number of sales between 2014 to 2017 with sales totalling to 229,855&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Table showing the number of sales between 2014 to 2017 with sales totalling to 229,855.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the majority of property transfers are residential, there are a range of complex sales that are harder to facilitate and process. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Farm sales&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Subdivisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apartments and unit titles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commercial buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Earthquake prone buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maori leasehold land&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leasehold titles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trust and trustee changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Result of river changing boundaries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-notice-and-its-importance-to-nz-inc&quot;&gt;The notice and its importance to NZ Inc&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notice directly help contribute to understanding New Zealand’s Financial and Physical Capital as defined in &lt;a href=&quot;https://treasury.govt.nz/information-and-services/nz-economy/living-standards&quot;&gt;Treasury’s Living Standards Framework&lt;/a&gt; (LSF). This framework draws on OECD analysis of wider indicators of wellbeing with the starting point is answering three questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are current outcomes?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will these outcomes be sustained or improved?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How resilient is the system?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LSF is based on four capitals that organise indicators of sustainable intergenerational
Wellbeing and for the notice Financial and Physical Capital is most applicable. This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial and physical capital includes the buildings, machines and equipment and other
conventional investment, including capital spending by government.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The financial assets of households provide resilience to unexpected life events and retirement.
&lt;strong&gt;Housing&lt;/strong&gt; is a major contributor to current wellbeing and is the highest-valued household asset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we link the information contained in the notice and use this with other data sources and use this for measuring the health and resilience of New Zealand properties and therefore contribute to Financial and Physical Capital wellbeing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is an opportunity to use the notice of sale data linked with the core rating valuation data to provide profiles of the housing stock of New Zealand ie that is we know the owner/occupier vs rentals, type of housing, construction, age, spacial (ie where they are located). What else could the data be mashed up with? What stories could this tell and what it could inform?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;open-data&quot;&gt;Open data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notice of sale information is deemed to be ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.data.govt.nz/open-data/what-is-open-data/&quot;&gt;open data&lt;/a&gt;’ ie it’s data anyone can use and share. It has an open licence, is openly accessible and is both human-readable and machine-readable.
To protect the integrity of the property sector the data needs to be made available to aid with transparency and avoid corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Design Intensive
The challenge for the Notice of Sale design intensive was to explore what a positive, effective customer experience looks like when based on a real-world &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/showcase/integrated-services-service-innovation-working-group/&quot;&gt;life event&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/blog/labplus-the-value-of-a-life-events-lens-a-vehicle-for-creating-long-term-strategic-value/&quot;&gt;see this blog post about the value of life events&lt;/a&gt;). The design team sought to understanding the big picture associated with notice of sale and where it fits within the life event of selling and buying a home and together seek to understand the desired outcome from different perspectives and identify indicative opportunities to achieve these outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representatives from Whangarei District Council, Auckland Council, Tauranga City Council, Wellington City Council, LINZ and the Service Innovation Lab (the Lab) were involved as team members involved either before and/or during the three day intensive between 13-15 August.
During the intensive we wanted to explore in the design sprint:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High level understanding of where the notice of sale fits within the life event of selling and buying a property&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate a collective understanding of the goals we seek for notice of sale.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reveal the pain-points, opportunities and constraints for the customer, agents, third parties and government agencies teams and understand what their motivations are.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reveal service bottlenecks, dead ends and successful interactions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explore any possible outcomes that could be developed that ease the pain-points&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explore if there is an opportunity for reusable components to be created&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the three days of the intensive we covered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 1: Gather&lt;/strong&gt; – Outline the complex problem, goals sought, audiences involved and their motivations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 2: Define&lt;/strong&gt; – Assess problems, opportunities and constraints, themes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 3: Ideate&lt;/strong&gt; / Visualize – Scenarios for our audiences and how we might make change&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is based on the following logic mapping flow model&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;(as shown below) developed by Dr Hazel Bradshaw from the Service Innovation Lab:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Complex Problem;Overarching Goal;Audience Types;Motivation(Intrinsic &amp;amp; Extrinsic);Problem/Pain Points;Constraints;Emerging Concepts;IDEATE.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Logic Mapping Flow diagram. Starts with Complex Problem; Overarching Goal; Audience Types; Motivation(Intrinsic); Motivation (Extrinsic); Problem/Pain Points; Constraints; Emerging Concepts; and lastly IDEATE.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-complex-problem&quot;&gt;The complex problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buying and selling a property is complicated transaction, it requires information to be exchanged between a number of parties and if errors are made it has consequences for property ratings and valuations. This can lead to stress and have financial implications for the parties particularly the property buyer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team considered this complex problem and were asked to consider the life event in the context of the notice of sale. Here are the themes the team identified:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;target-theme---automation&quot;&gt;Target theme - Automation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theme selected as a focus point was Automation. The team would like to automate as much of the current manual process as possible to improve the quality of submissions. They’d like to get rid of the term “notice of sale” from their vocabulary to allow time to focus on more important or higher value interactions with ratepayers and clients. They’s like to to see data entered once and transmitted electronically to all the stakeholders involved in the process (preferably from a single place). It was noted that automation should not be at the expense of verification, accuracy and completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-themes-in-order-of-importance-to-the-team&quot;&gt;Other themes in order of importance to the team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Single source of truth.&lt;/strong&gt; There is no current single source of authoritative data for the notice of sale that anyone can draw from eg no one reference number that follows a ownership transfer for parties to use. Team were quite fixed on this as a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data quality.&lt;/strong&gt; This includes accuracy and completeness. This involves changes in ownership that were not notified to the council or were lost somehow plus the accuracy of the received notices and its input into multiple systems. The discussion also revealed that there is also a need for more information that is needed to complete tasks that is not in the mandated information that must be sent. Eg contact details, postal addresses. The consequences of data quality include the number of manual checks and validation points throughout the process. Most systems also cater for happy day scenarios too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Timeliness.&lt;/strong&gt; The team advised they need the notice information to be supplied as soon as possible to allow more value add tasks to be completed eg audit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improving council experience.&lt;/strong&gt; Because the notice is a a major part of the councils rates and valuation teams business, it takes up a large chunk of their time and they’d love to streamline the work for the sake of accuracy, auditing and sanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improved customer experience.&lt;/strong&gt; The team are passionate about making life better and easier for our customers. From a solicitor perspective it’s about the desire to improve the process for the profession and their clients. Hopefully improvements will lead to an increase in trust between all parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data transmission.&lt;/strong&gt; The notice needs to be sent to many parties, how could this be made easier? How do we make it more user friendly for solicitors to provide information?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goal-setting----what-are-the-end-goals&quot;&gt;Goal setting  - What are the end goals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team considered the goals associated with the complex problem statement - why is a goal important for this work? what does it look like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These end goals were identified for the notice both from a higher level and a specific goal to focus on for this design intensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The higher level goals were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will improve the accuracy of sales and owner information that will ultimately result in better rating valuations and revaluations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consistent, complete information that drives decision making and innovation - one source of truth for all market participants eg buyers and sellers, real estate agents, councils, central government.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better data helps contribute to better economic outcomes especially considering how property is a big driver in NZ economic success.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helps improve the quality of house  and property owners interactions with Council - often their first contact is a compliant due to an error with the rates and valuations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved service for people involved in sales and transfers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal selected for the intensive was &lt;strong&gt;Data Quality&lt;/strong&gt; - this is needed for the rating and valuation tasks. This includes missing sales, accuracy of the data received and needing more information beyond the current notice rules to complete tasks.  It was recognised that to help with the theme of Automation data quality will be a key enabler. From this there were some sub goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Efficiency of process for everyone to free up people up to do higher value things/work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trust in data and process integrity to meet compliance requirements and ensure confidence for property owners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related themes to data quality (in order of importance) were accuracy and completeness of the notice, verified data within the notice and  ability for data sources to be linked. Other themes were improving the process within Councils, efficiency of process for all parties by creating less touch points and making compliance with the process easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was noted that data quality would help mitigate the problems people encounter that are represented in the other themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;audience-mapping&quot;&gt;Audience Mapping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;primary audience&lt;/strong&gt; for the goals and theme is Council teams plus the agents (solicitor / conveyancer) who facilitates the notice for property buyers and sellers. Their relationship is key to the notice process being completed and sent to Council but also how issues are identified and resolved together. There is also a difference in expectations between the two regarding the amount of data that needs to be supplied to ensure that the new owner of property is correctly identified and billed the right amount of rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Council teams&lt;/strong&gt; included: customer data coordinators, customer services staff, digital capture, revenue, mailroom, credit control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the &lt;strong&gt;agents&lt;/strong&gt; this also extends to their professional bodies, individual practices, legal executives and secretaries, juniors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;secondary audience&lt;/strong&gt; is LINZ most notably the OVR, Valuation Service Providers and third party utilities that directly need the NoS eg Watercare. These groups are essential for the valuation of properties and the notice is seen as the “&lt;em&gt;life blood&lt;/em&gt;” of rating valuation and “&lt;em&gt;without it we have nothing&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customers were considered to be the the old and new owners of the property, third parties who consume the data, ratepayers, real estate agents, government agencies who consume the data, software developers, office of auditor general. These groups of customers are impacted by the notice especially if there is issues with the data quality for a property but for the most part they will not be directly affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;motivation-mapping---intrinsic-and-extrinsic&quot;&gt;Motivation Mapping - Intrinsic and extrinsic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table showing the Intrinsic &amp;amp; Extrinsic motivations for Primary audiences (Councils &amp;amp; Solicitors) and secondary audiences&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Table showing the Intrinsic &amp;amp; Extrinsic motivations for Primary audiences (Councils &amp;amp; Solicitors) and Secondary audiences.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problems-the-audiences-are-having&quot;&gt;Problems the audiences are having&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To consider the problems the various audiences are having the team were asked to map out the journeys for the solicitors and council teams. Prior to the intensive, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/drawings/d/1_V6L9ibgHlJ8Fyc0Id6uJQlFdc0_XDsV1R5yDxxP81o/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;service blueprint&lt;/a&gt; describing the journey from presale triggers to post-sale settlement was created and this was used by the team as a reference for their maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Flow diagram of Process. Pre-Sale; Sale &amp;amp; Purchase agreement signed; Unconditional; Settlement; &amp;amp; Post-settlement&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Flow diagram of the Notice of Sale Process. Pre-Sale; Sale &amp;amp; Purchase agreement signed; Unconditional; Settlement (can be up to 6 months before Settlement); &amp;amp; Post-settlement.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/14wHVvtWVUsMaPOQZZ6hXXLu37Yir56DT/view&quot;&gt;Solicitor journey map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Post-it notes for Journey Map. Votes on Education/Action Points; &amp;amp; Unreliable Data&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Post-it notes for Journey Map. Votes on Education/Action Points; &amp;amp; Unreliable Data.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Post-it notes for Journey Map. Votes on Incorrect or Missing Data; Human Error; &amp;amp; Duplicating Information&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Post-it notes for Journey Map. Votes on Incorrect or Missing Data; Human Error; &amp;amp; Duplicating Information.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/14wHVvtWVUsMaPOQZZ6hXXLu37Yir56DT/view&quot;&gt;Council journey map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS9.png&quot; alt=&quot;Post-it notes for Journey Map. Top votes on Manual processing/checking including multiple handling of the notice&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Post-it notes for Journey Map. Top votes on Manual processing/checking including multiple handling of the notice.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey maps revealed a range of pain points. The pain point themes were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Education and knowledge at key action points&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unreliable data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Problem themes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Duplication of information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human error&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incorrect or missing data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The notice is not received&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manual processing/checking including multiple handling of the notice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Difficult to find and match data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Churn - checking, comms, rework&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These selected themes were turned into &lt;strong&gt;problem statements&lt;/strong&gt; using the following format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a [audience type] the problem I (or we) have is [pain point]. This impacts my ability to [task or outcome the audience is trying to solve].&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem statements were consider and themed to identify common elements with the top three themes consolidated into these problem statements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem-statement-one---accurate-and-complete-information&quot;&gt;Problem statement one - accurate and complete information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a solicitor, I have a problem with providing accurate and complete information to councils about the property being sold, transferred or changed eg its location address and the Council or Territorial Local Authority and about the property owner (eg their name and contact details incl their postal address, email, mobile number). This impacts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my ability to meet my client needs, to do a good job and ensure my compliance with the rules.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Council’s ability to efficiently process changes to property data, rating database and comply with rules&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Council’s ability to contact property owners&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Council workers ability to do a good job, deliver a good service to ratepayers and improve the Council’s reputation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each problem statement the team considered if there are any constraints associated with it and how hard it might be to resolve them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table matching Ability to resolve a constraint (Easy; Medium; Hard) with Constraints&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Table matching Ability to resolve a constraint (Easy; Medium; Hard) with Constraints.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem-statement-two---manual-processing&quot;&gt;Problem statement two - manual processing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Council administrator, me and my team leaders have a problem with the large amount of manual processing to complete the input of the notice of sale. This impacts our ability to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;approach this task with enthusiasm and makes my job boring&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;save money for ratepayers that could be better spent on things in my community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work well with solicitors, who through our processing errors will have difficulties with their clients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS11.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table matching Ability to resolve a constraint (Easy; Medium; Hard) with Constraints&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Table matching Ability to resolve a constraint (Easy; Medium; Hard) with Constraints.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem-statement-three---triggers-for-notice-of-sale&quot;&gt;Problem statement three - triggers for notice of sale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Solicitor the problem I have is that I don’t know all the triggers for the Notice of Sale and its importance to rates and valuations. This impacts my ability to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;meet my clients needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work with councils and their need for information for rates and valuations, payments and refunds and debt collection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS12.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table matching Ability to resolve a constraint (Easy; Medium; Hard) with Constraints&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Table matching Ability to resolve a constraint (Easy; Medium; Hard) with Constraints.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team believe that if these problems were fixed then it could resolve many of the problems described in the other themes. These other themes that resulted from the creation of the problem statements were data input and matching, manual processing and validation, not sending or receiving the notice, the impacts of errors and the impacts to the value of the team and individuals within it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scenario-and-storyboard-building---exploring-problems-and-solutions&quot;&gt;Scenario and storyboard building - exploring problems and solutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explore problems and solutions for these scenario and storyboard techniques were used. The team created a scenario that addresses the audience problem, meets the a clear goal and works within the constraints. A scenario should have an audience, a goal, a set of constraints and a beginning, middle and an end. These were themed and storyboards were created based on the prioritised scenarios.
Each person shared their &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1n0p7UeOUayG6tX-tSddJavi2JoKMsUql/view&quot;&gt;storyboards&lt;/a&gt; and then team was separated into groups who took the scenarios, identified their common elements and collaborated to create a refined storyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS13.png&quot; alt=&quot;Team collaborated to create a refined storyboard from the common elements of the scenarios&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS14.png&quot; alt=&quot;Team collaborated to create a refined storyboard from the common elements of the scenarios&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Team collaborated to create a refined storyboard from the common elements of the scenarios.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problem-statement-one---accurate-and-complete-information-1&quot;&gt;Problem statement one - accurate and complete information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of scenarios were created and many had similar themes. Here are the priorised themes las decided by the group:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Property transfer in a single portal - data validated against authoritative datasets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accurate ratepayer contact information - education of ratepayers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Correct Correct or territorial local authority selected  - against an authoritative dataset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tied with no votes: Councils validate their databases against authoritative datasets, solicitors validates data against authoritative sources, accurate ratepayer contact information - verified against authoritative datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1wHK0CyhgpjKDqbMnyVFmCID0NsYliwyd/view&quot;&gt;storyboards&lt;/a&gt; for the property transfer in a single portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS15.png&quot; alt=&quot;Storyboard for the Property Transfer made up of post-it notes&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS16.png&quot; alt=&quot;Storyboard for the Property Transfer made up of post-it notes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Storyboard for the Property Transfer made up of post-it notes.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This storyboard was ultimately the one selected to &lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-PossibleSolution&quot;&gt;explore further&lt;/a&gt; during the rest of the design intensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problem-statement-two---manual-processing-1&quot;&gt;Problem statement two - manual processing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of scenarios were created but they had a similar theme - property transfer in a single portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the storyboards for the property transfer in a single portal. For the refined storyboard because of the similarity with those created in statement one, they should be combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problem-statement-three---triggers-for-notice-of-sale-1&quot;&gt;Problem statement three - triggers for notice of sale&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two themes that were tied in priority:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve communication between Councils and Solicitors - spending time together&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rules and data validation flags to help select the correct process to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1wHK0CyhgpjKDqbMnyVFmCID0NsYliwyd/view&quot;&gt;refined storyboards&lt;/a&gt;. The team believed that these ideas could be something that could be done within each Council and trialling the approach with local law firms and conveyancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improve communication between Council and Solicitors - ‘spending time together’
 &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS17.png&quot; alt=&quot;Storyboard - Improve communication between Council and Solicitors - ‘spending time together’&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rules and data validation flags to help select the correct process to use.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS18.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rules and data validation flags to help select the correct process to use&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-solution&quot;&gt;Possible solution&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-PossibleSolution&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea behind this possible future state is that much of the data required to action what is currently called the ‘Notice of Sale’ process is captured within the Sales and Purchase Agreement or through the Transfer Instrument (see &lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Appendix2&quot;&gt;Appendix 2 Data Map&lt;/a&gt; for what data is collected at each step in the process). There are different triggers for this process (see the &lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Appendix1&quot;&gt;triggers in Appendix 1&lt;/a&gt;), which is actually the process of changing the ownership of a rating unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than expecting each person in the process chain to perform manual data entry then we could imagine a process where the data is kept as electronic data and systematically pushed through the required states of a workflow. Ideally this would satisfy the legislative requirements (see &lt;a href=&quot;#Go-to-Appendix1&quot;&gt;Appendix 1 for the key concepts required under legislation&lt;/a&gt;) while achieving the goal of improved data quality and improved trust in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS19.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flow diagram describing the Change of Ownership of a Rating Unit - Future State version 0.2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Flow diagram describing the Change of Ownership of a Rating Unit - Future State version 0.2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This future state needs deeper investigation to determine its desirability, viability and feasibility, and would necessarily involve a slow transition, including improving data quality within the various databases over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.agilealliance.org/glossary/mvp/#q=~(filters~(tags~(~'mvp))~searchTerm~'~sort~false~sortDirection~'asc~page~1)&quot;&gt;Minimum Viable Product&lt;/a&gt; might involve manual data entry from the Sales and Purchase Agreement into a data integration tool, or an upload of a data extract from a smart form version of the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-NextSteps&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The group discussed the need for a sponsor(s) to help drive continuing this work. It was agreed that the sponsor could be a person or group of people but they should be at be at an executive leadership level eg a CFO. The group of councils involved with this exploration will need to work together to identify a sponsor(s) and brief them on this work and its importance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Depending on the priorities for the 2018/19 Service Innovation Lab work programme, the Lab could lead a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digital.govt.nz/standards-and-guidance/strategy-and-planning/digital-lifecycle/discovery/&quot;&gt;discovery&lt;/a&gt; with the support of this group to investigate the possible solution in more detail to test its viability, feasibility and desirability.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Councils collectively or individually could investigate the other two opportunities identified in the intensive; Improve communication between Councils and Solicitors - spending time together and Rules and data validation flags to help select the correct process to use. The team believed that these ideas could be something that could be done within each Council and trialling the approach with local law firms and conveyancers. This is being currently being explored further collective team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;appendix-1--notice-of-sale-context-diagram&quot;&gt;Appendix 1 &lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Appendix1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Notice of Sale Context Diagram&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This diagram maps out the relevant concepts in the legislation relating to Notice of Sale to help with understanding the current legislative requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To read the diagram follow the arrows, i.e Ratepayer (Owner and/or Lessee) owns or occupies Rating Unit; Rating Unit created, maintained and held in District Valuation Roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS20.png&quot; alt=&quot;Diagram of concepts in leglislation relating to the Notice of Sale process&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Diagram of concepts in leglislation relating to the Notice of Sale process.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Triggers for notice of change of ownership of a rating unit
Although commonly referred to as a “notice of sale”, that’s actually a bit of a misnomer as it not just sales that trigger the need for a notice.  Broadly speaking, there are four triggers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If an owner sells or otherwise transfers a rating unit or any part of a rating unit (section 31(1) Local Government (Rating) Act 2002);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a person becomes the owner of a rating unit by operation of law (section 31(3) Local Government (Rating) Act 2002);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Registration of a change of name of a rating unit (section 36 Local Government (Rating) Act 2002); and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transfer, assignment, surrender or termination of lease (sections 32 and 33 of the Local Government (Rating) Act 2002).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of a sale of a rating unit, Section 31 of the Local Government (Rating) Act 2002 provides that a vendor or, if the vendor has an agent, the vendor’s agent must, within one month of the effective date of sale or transfer, provide the relevant local authority with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the full name and address of the purchaser; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the case of a sale, the sale price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legislation does not mandate the form in which the notice is provided.  Additionally, there is no definition of “sale price”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all other cases, the transferor (former owner) must notify Council of the change in owner of the rating unit.  Again, the legislation does not mandate the form in which the notice is provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So which instruments trigger the need for a Notice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sale of a property which results in the registration of a transfer instrument is the most obvious trigger for a Notice, but it’s far from the only one.  Other common transactions which trigger need for a Notice include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dealing with an estate resulting in registration of a Transmission (instrument quick code TSM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A mortgagee sale resulting in registration of a Transfer in exercise of Power of Sale (instrument quick code TPS);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Registration of a Joint Family Home application (instrument quick code JFH); and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A change of name of an owner (due to marriage or a company changing its name) (instrument quick code CN).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, there are a number of less common transactions that could trigger need for a Notice – some of which are incredibly rear.  For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transferring assets on the winding up of an Incorporated Society resulting in registration of an application under section 27 of the Incorporated Societies Act 1908 (instrument quick code A27);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An application for accretion as a result of changing river boundaries (instrument quick code ACC);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An application under section 99A of the Land Transfer Act 1952 to record a statutory vesting (instrument quick code A99A); and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An application to transfer land as a result of the Health Sector (Transfers) Act 1993 (instrument quick code A9).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;appendix-2--notice-of-sale-data-map&quot;&gt;Appendix 2 &lt;a name=&quot;Go-to-Appendix2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Notice of Sale Data Map&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows what data points are collected through what mechanism at different points in the sale or change of ownership process, and what the data source is and where it goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS21.png&quot; alt=&quot;Notice of Sale Data Map&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS22.png&quot; alt=&quot;Notice of Sale Data Map&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS23.png&quot; alt=&quot;Notice of Sale Data Map&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS24.png&quot; alt=&quot;Notice of Sale Data Map&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/Exploring-the-Notice-of-Sale-Process/ETNS25.png&quot; alt=&quot;Notice of Sale Data Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Notice of Sale Data Map.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this report, Local Authorities will be referred to as Councils. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bradshaw, H. (2014). The Structural Playability Process (SPP )-An Effective Design Process for Educational Computer Games. chp 3, p60 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>glen-thurston</name></author><category term="lessons learned" /></entry></feed>